<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands new-yeares gift, or, A pearle for a prince: with such grapes from thornes, and fruits from foes, to the whole land, as none shall be worse for wrongs, nor hurt by any but themselves, though the times should prove worse and worse.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E424_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864025</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E424[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands new-yeares gift, or, A pearle for a prince: with such grapes from thornes, and fruits from foes, to the whole land, as none shall be worse for wrongs, nor hurt by any but themselves, though the times should prove worse and worse.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Austin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 31 1647"; the 8 in imprint date crossed out and date altered to 1647.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116244:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS New-yeares Gift, <hi>OR,</hi> A Pearle for a Prince: WITH Such Grapes from Thornes, and Fruits from Foes, to the whole Land, as none ſhall be worſe for wrongs, nor hurt by any but themſelves, though the times ſhould prove worſe and worſe.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Tolle &amp; lege.</hi> 
               <bibl>Auguſtinus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Et experto crede</hi> 
               <bibl>Hieronimo <hi>ex Hibernia Redivivo.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Auſtin.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116244:2"/>
            <head>To every paſsive Reader.</head>
            <l>TO all, who parallell me with their wrong'd ſelves,</l>
            <l>In two climes ſhorne, torn, ſplit on rocks and ſhelves:</l>
            <l>Beſt fruits from foes, this paper preſent ſhewes,</l>
            <l>From mine own bowells drawn, as Silkwormes Clewes:</l>
            <l>Chiefe here my kindneſſe creeps, which cannot goe</l>
            <l>To all my <hi>Brides</hi> firme Friends, from whom, my Foe,</l>
            <l>Satan divorc'd me long: though love regaines</l>
            <l>Spleens loſſe, if Sectaries forbid not baines.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116244:2"/>
            <head>Englands New-years-Gift, or a Pearle for a Prince.</head>
            <p>IT is reported of Doctor <hi>Ridley,</hi> a faith-ſealing Martyr, that the onely way to make him a mans friend, was to doe him an ill turne, at leaſt this was the way to gaine his prayers. Parallel to his practiſe was the Counſell, that M. <hi>Omſtead</hi> lately (a zealous Preacher in Ireland) gave to one that complained of ſome emulating ſneaks, or ſnakes of his owne Tribe, who had ſtung him by detraction, and bit him with a dogged and Theonine tooth, that if he might adviſe him in this caſe, he ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goe to the Throne of Grace and powre out his ſoule in prayer for him, as <hi>David</hi> put on ſackcloth and mourned for his enemies, even ſuch as <hi>Saul Doeg</hi> and <hi>Achitophel;</hi> and this is all the revenge he would take on them, as the beſt way withall to doe himſelfe good, ſince to do evill for evill, this was Paganiſh and Brutiſh, one Dog, Wolfe and Fox tearing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring another: to doe good for good was carnall and naturall, <hi>manus manum fricat, &amp; mulus ſcabit mulum,</hi> one hand rubs another, one ſcabb'd mule knaps another, one good turne requires and requites another; to doe evill for good, as <hi>Judas</hi> did to Chriſt, and <hi>Laffin</hi> the falſe friend to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron the French <hi>Byron,</hi> and as ſome Favorites and Traytors to their Kings, bringing downe like Elder trees the walls in and by which they grew, as the Cuckow teares the kind hedge Sparrow who bred her and fed her, this is vile and viperous, yea diabolicall; but to good for evill, and to overcome evill with good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. this is truly Angelicall, the higheſt pitch of Chriſtianity, ſympathizing with <hi>Abraham,</hi> who prayed for <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> that would have wronged him in his wife, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. with the Prophet whoſe prayer reſtored that withered hand of <hi>Jeroboams,</hi> which was ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out againſt him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13. with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> who improved their beſt to ſave the ſoule of that cruell Jailor, who whipped and abuſed their bodies, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. yea to Chriſt himſelfe, who healed the eare of <hi>Malchus,</hi> one of his riotous and rigorous apprehenders, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.10. and in this caſe of retaliating or remitting injuries, as <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> the Epirote, and many more which might be hiſtorified, gained friends from foes, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the two <hi>Scipioes,</hi> Aſian and African, ſo I would have it ſeriouſly poized, that as patience is the moſt heroick fortitude, overcoming a mans ſelfe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116244:3"/>more then others, as <hi>fortius eſt qui ſe, quàm qui fortiſſima vincit,</hi> ſo impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency is the greateſt follie, yea a madneſſe fit to be whipped in Bedlam; for a man not to take his croſſe quietly, and to bear it with <hi>Simon Cyreneus</hi> after Chriſt, but to make his Croſſe heavier by his owne fretting, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fuming then it is in it own nature, as <hi>Thales</hi> his Aſſe made her burden of wool heavier by laying her ſelfe downe with it in the water, as before ſhe had melted her load of ſalt lighter by the like poſture, as if a man ſhould give me a box on the one eare, I ſhould give my ſelfe a box on the other, or lay another load on my right ſhoulder, becauſe a heavy burden is impoſed on my left; impatiency being ſuch a ſalve for every fore, as ſoute, inke and tarre is to the waſhing of a foule face to make it ſeem faire, or as the cutting of the thumb or the toe is medicineable to the curing of the Gout.</p>
            <p>But if by patience and penitence thou live like ſome fire-flies called <hi>Pyruuſtae,</hi> in brazen furnaces, in the heat of moſt ſcorching croſſes, and come out of them as gold out of the fire more pure, with the droſſe and tin of thy hereditary corruptions more purged by the ſpirit of fire and of burning, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 4. then thy moſt inteſtine and inveterate foes muſt doe thee good whether they will or no, even ſore againſt their wills; like that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who reſolving to kill his enemie in a Duell, by running his ſword into his breſt, ſo cured him of an Impoſtume which he broke, that he made him a ſounder man then ever he was; as it is ſaid of a bone, that after breaking is ſoundly knit, proves ſtronger then it was before; to this purpoſe of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſummer fruits from tempeſtuous and winter foes, (as <hi>Virgil</hi> gathered gold from <hi>Ennius</hi> his droſſe, as <hi>Plato</hi> had a curb for his pride, by <hi>Diogenes</hi> trampling on his bed with greater pride, and as from the very oyle of Scorpions the Italians are ſaid to reſerve Antidotes againſt the ſtinging of Scorpions, and Surgeons to cure the bitings of mad Dogs, from the very livers of the ſaid dead Dogs,) ſo I heard of a patient and religious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that being unequally yoaked and peſtered with a wife, little better then <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Zepporah, Socrates</hi> his <hi>Xantippe,</hi> or <hi>Jobs</hi> wife, (thought to be <hi>Dinah,</hi>) as ſoon as ever her waſpiſh and aſpiſh ſpirit was ſo conjured up, that ſhe gave him his broth all ſcalding hot, and ſcorched him with her tongues wild-fire, immediately he fled from her as from a Snake, and reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe into a wood or ſolitary grove, where in his devout ſoliloquies he powred out his ſoule unto God in mentall and ejaculatory prayer; in this and the like patterns of imitation and vertuous emulation, <hi>quod cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam id cuivis,</hi> it is eaſie for any man in the like caſes or croſſes, inriched with the like graces of prayer, patience, and penitence, to gather the like figs from thiſtles, the like roſes of ſweet refections from the briers, bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116244:3"/>and nettles of the like afflictions, the like golden fruits from the like croſſe and cankred foes, more precious then any hiſtorified or poetized fruits in the Gardens of <hi>Adonis,</hi> or the Orchards of the <hi>Heſperides,</hi> kept ſo ſtrictly by waking Dragons, or Gryphins, <hi>oh fortunati nimium ſi ſua bona norint,</hi> happy are the patient in what kind ſoever paſſive, all the waves that bluſter againſt this rocke of patience, more excellent then all the white cliffie rocks in our Albion beſides, however impetuous in theſe tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and toſſing times, they doe but daſh themſelves to ſome and froth, and waſh it whiter, as the accuſations of <hi>Potyphars</hi> wife, <hi>Phedra</hi> and the goatiſh Judges did the innocency of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Hippolitus</hi> and <hi>Suſanna;</hi> the raging waves indeed, and wraths of Tyrants, and hell-hatched Hereticks may bluſter againſt the out-ſide of the Church built on Chriſt the true Rock, as the ſtormes beat againſt the out-walls of a houſe, a Pallace, or a Temple, but they diſturb not nor diſtract not the Inhabitants or Sojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners within; the inſides of Rocks are not penetrated by the moſt roaring and ſurging ſeas, enemies indeed like ſerpents and toads, and ravenous beaſts, may <hi>manducare terram,</hi> lick this duſt of ours, feed as wolves on Carrion, on our outward mould, our terreſtriall part; <hi>but ultra alam for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae,</hi> they hurt our ſoules no more (if ſanctified, anchored, and ſetled in our preſent Fluctuations) then a ſword or a ſpeare doth a ſpirit or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, or the chop of an axe the beames of the Sun which ſhine upon a blocke; now what great hurt is there in the cracking of a ſhell, and the ſaving of the kernell, in the loſſe of a rotten purſe, (emblemes of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) the ſoul, like pure gold being reſerved and preſerved ſafe.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Zuinglius</hi> that zealous Belgick Light, received his deaths wound in the wars of the Quinque Pagi about Religion, his laſt words (as his <hi>ultimum vale</hi>) to the world were theſe, <hi>Corpus occidi poteſt animam occidere non poſſunt,</hi> my enemies can kill my body, but they cannot kill the ſoule, this <hi>divinae, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticula aurae,</hi> this celeſtiall heavenly infuſed ſoule, as it is immateriall, ſo it is no more penetrable by any terreſtriall weapons then the Sun, the Moon, the Planets and the Angells and Intelligences which more them, this ſoule is <hi>extra alam,</hi> beyond the power of Tyranny and Cruelty, a note above the Ela of humane hoſtilitie, <hi>tunde Anaxarchi Vaſculum Anaxarchum non laedis,</hi> a <hi>Phalaris</hi> a <hi>Buſiris,</hi> an <hi>Anacreon</hi> may knock in pieces the out-veſſell, the out-cask, the out-cabinet, the out-cage of the body, the continent of the ſoule: but the ſoule it ſelfe which is in a manner <hi>totum hominis</hi> the whole man or the beſt of man, this inward wine they cannot tilt, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed Pearle of Pearles (better worth then a world) they cannot plunder, this Phoenix, this bird of Paradiſe, they cannot kill; though the lightning which we ſee, and the thunder that we heare breaking the incloſed clouds,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116244:4"/>chiefly the condenſate bolt oft breake the bones and the mettled ſword without any great ſignalls on the fleſh or the ſcabberd, according to <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> yet when truculent Tyrants ſpeak <hi>lapides &amp; fulmina,</hi> ſtones and fire-bolts, and lighten and thunder, as <hi>Jezabel</hi> once againſt <hi>Elias, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxia</hi> that ſecond <hi>Herodias</hi> againſt S. <hi>Chriſoſtome, Innocent</hi> or <hi>Nocent</hi> the third againſt the Emperour <hi>Otho, Innocent</hi> the fourth againſt <hi>Fredericke, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the ſecond againſt <hi>Leo Iſaurus, Zacharias</hi> againſt the French <hi>Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, Pius</hi> (or <hi>Impius</hi>) <hi>Quintus</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> yet theſe <hi>Bruta Fulmina,</hi> as the French Authour derides them,<note n="a" place="margin">See the Booke called <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Fulmen.</hi>
               </note> and our <hi>Rof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſis</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Adverſus Bellarminum, pag. <hi>944.</hi> &amp; pag. <hi>974.</hi>
               </note>, theſe roaring Bulls of Baſan, theſe ſquibs and fire-workes, how ere like <hi>Davuſſes</hi> or Devills, they diſturbed the peace of their States and Kingdomes, as their Incendiaries and Fire-brands the Jeſuits, have ſet all in a Phaetonian confuſion in <hi>Moravia, Helvetia, Sileſia, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, France, England, and Ireland:</hi> yet they wrought and brought no more prejudice to ſanctified ſoules then the curſes of the Witch <hi>Balaam</hi> to Gods owne Iſraelites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.19, 20. Hence it was a wiſe Conſolatory ſpeech of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> to his daughters <hi>Livia</hi> and <hi>Julia,</hi> telling him that all the people of Rome ſpoke evill of them, he thanking his Gods, that though they ſpoke evill of them, yet it was not in their power to doe them any evill,<note place="margin">Apud Plutarchum.</note> and therefore wiſhed them to ſuffer free ſpeech in a free Citie, which free ſpeech all the wit and worth of man, yea of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency it ſelfe, can no more curb in malignant minds and mouthes, then they can ſtay the winds, or ſtint the waves, or ſhackle the Helleſpont, or do ſuch impoſſible things, as once <hi>Xerxes</hi> and <hi>Canutus</hi> attempted, ſince Lions have been tamed, and Elephants in the warres of King <hi>Porus</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> Otters have been tamed like Water-Spaniels, Ravens have been tamed and lured as Hawks, Wolves and Foxes, wild and vild Dogs, have been tamed as houſhold Curres, Quoy-ducks have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to deceive the tame; ſo Storks, Cranes, Crowes<note n="c" place="margin">Ave Caeſar.</note>, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinjayes, all kind of birds, and ſome kinds of Serpents and Fiſhes<note n="d" place="margin">See inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins de Lapi de in cap. <hi>3.</hi> Jacobi.</note>; but the tongue-like Panthers and Field-mice is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domable without the help of <hi>Mors</hi> and <hi>Morpheus,</hi> death and deadly ſleep: Angells men and Devills cannot tame it, the wild fire in it kindled from hell, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.6. like the coales of Juniper, yea like hell-fire it ſelfe unquenchable: the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of an <hi>Elias</hi> counted a troubler of Iſrael, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17. of <hi>Paul</hi> held a factious fellow, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.5. of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of Hippolitus the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116244:4"/>Paganiſh <hi>Joſeph;</hi> of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> of <hi>Abner,</hi> of <hi>Eugenius,</hi> accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of incontinency, of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> called <hi>Sathanaſius,</hi> and taxed as a Murtherer<note n="c" place="margin">Apud Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg paſſim.</note> of <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Scipio,</hi> oft produced and traduced before the Romane Senate: of S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> branded by the Prieſts of Rome<note n="d" place="margin">Of which he complains in many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles.</note> for his holy and honeſt converſing with <hi>Paula, Paulina, Euſtochium, Demetriades</hi> and other chaſt Matrons and Maids, yea the purity of Chriſt himſelfe conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Publicans and Sinners (as the Sun ſhines upon Quagmires and rotten Bogs without any contamination) could cauſe none of theſe to eſcape the aſperſions and calumnies of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing tongues, no more then the Sun and the Moon can muzzle the barkings of ſome dogs againſt their luſterous ſhines, as <hi>Doegs</hi> and emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating <hi>Momiſts</hi> and <hi>Zoiliſts</hi> ſtill will bark, <hi>invita Minerva,</hi> againſt ſhining gifts and graces, and places amongſt Arts and Armes, yet as we have a greater and more certaine tutelary God, then <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignely thanke this God, that though in unbloudy perſecutions we daily heare the mocks of Romiſh <hi>Michols,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20. the railing of Atheiſticall and Papiſticall <hi>Rabſhakehs,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.22. the flouts of rejected <hi>Iſmaels, Gen.</hi> 21.9. the curſes of Sathanicall <hi>Shemcis,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. the ſcoffes of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Tobiahs, Nehem.</hi> 4.3. and <hi>Sanballats,</hi> all haters of God, of the godly and of all goodneſſe, all oppoſers, Remoraes and obſtacles of Religion and Reformation, all as inteſtine enemies to all of the houſe of <hi>David, Zech.</hi> 12.8.9. all <hi>Ezekiaſſes, Ezraes</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> who would rebuild and purge our polluted Temples, as ever <hi>Hanniball</hi> was unto the Romanes a ſworne Antagoniſt; or <hi>Haman</hi> the curſed Amalekite to <hi>Eſther, Mardocheus</hi> and all the religious Jewes, yet <hi>Gratias ſuperis,</hi> God be praiſed, theſe whelps of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> though they barke and ſhew their tongues and their teeth, they cannot bite further then God pleaſes to unchaine them and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muzzle them, and ſet them upon us, for our playing the pranks of wild Heifers and indomable Bullocks, breaking over the hedges of all comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and limited obedience into forbidden paſtures, as <hi>David</hi> in his Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.9. and <hi>Solomon</hi> in his uxorious Idolatry, for which God ſet <hi>Abſalom, Semei, Sheba</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> againſt the one, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. &amp; 13. &amp; cap. 20. and <hi>Rezon</hi> and <hi>Iereboam</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.23. &amp; v. 26. againſt the other, all the Organs of evill to Sion, all the Factors and Agents for Antichriſt, for the Scarlet Whore, for the Prince of darkneſſe, chiefly in their unlawfull, luſtfull, and unlimited warres againſt the Saints, all and every one of them are under the power and command of the King of Sion, the Father of the Saints, he hath all the malignant powers, plots and policies of earth and hell, even Witches, Conjurers, and infernall ſpirits themſelves, all the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cering
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116244:5"/>Sorcering Maſſe-Prieſts and Friers of the Romiſh Hierarchie, and all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Nigromanticks at this day, the Lord of Hoſts hath them all as Wolves and Dogs in their chaines, as Lions in their grates, as roaring Bulls at their ſtakes, and Bears at their rings, he keeps them all in as Seas and rivers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their banks and bounds, or lets them out as in the inundations in <hi>Duca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> time, and in <hi>Noahs</hi> flood; he hath all created powers as ſtaves in his owne hands, as arrowes in his owne quiver, as <hi>David</hi> his ſtones in his ſting, to keep in or imploy at his pleaſure: he being the true <hi>Aeolus</hi> who hath all the winds in a bag, all the waves in a bank, all the wicked Hereticks and Tyrants within and without the Church, hooked by their noſes, as he had <hi>Pharoah, Senacherib, Rabſhekch,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 19.27, 28. <hi>Holofernes, Antiochus, Epiphanes,</hi> proud <hi>Coſroes, Saul</hi> before his converſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. cap. 22. &amp; 26. and all ſanginnolent perſecutors in all times, letting them play their reaks and pranks ſo long, till he got himſelfe a name upon them, either in the converſion of ſome few of them, or the confuſion of the moſt of them; when their ſinnes like the ſinnes of the Amorites <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.16. and Sodomites were at the full ripeneſſe, and fit for the ſickle of deſerved vengeance, this then is the firſt cordiall I give to the coroſives of the Saints, the firſt ground of comfort to our preſent mourners in Sion, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. the wicked which plow deep furrowes on our backs, God himſelfe yoakes them, they are but rods in the hands of our Father, but the Jailors and the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the will and decree of our Father Judge, as a moderne Divine ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alludes to God, they are but Gods Serjeants to arreſt us, for our undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged debts, our unrepented ſins, they cannot hurt us more then a ſword in the ſcabberd, till it be drawne and laid on by a valiant Martialiſt, being of it ſelfe a dead inſtrument without a living hand to weild it; as indeed the creature of it ſelfe, whether animate or manimate, can doe us neither good nor hurt, without the reſtraining or mannaging of the Creator, as Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi> hath lively demonſtrated as an experimentall Divine, in his golden work of Gods All-ſufficiency: and I have fully explained in the Book called <hi>the Arraignement of the Creature:</hi> And indeed this is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ground of comfort to all that by the ſpirit can cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. that their croſſes come from a Father, not from a ſevere Judge, that they are but love-tokens from the Bridegroom to his Spouſe, <hi>Rev,</hi> 3.19. hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pills from a Phyſitian, caſtigating rods and ferulaes in in the hand of a Father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7. as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid once in ſome reall or imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Delinquencies of her heroick <hi>Eſſex, ad correctionem non ad ruinam,</hi> to correction not to deſtruction; as Gods ſcourges were ſo Idolatrizing and Adulterizing <hi>Solomon,</hi> whom though he afflicted in the revolt of ten Tribes, and in excited enemies, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. yet he rejected not, he tooke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116244:5"/>not his mercy from him as from <hi>Saul</hi> the Reprobate, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.14. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1.14. Oh, this is indeed <hi>Oleum vulneris latificans Galeni, mell in ore melos in aure,</hi> as the phraſes be melodie to the eare, muſick to the mind, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the heart, yea as <hi>Roſa Solis</hi> and <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> to our dead ſownes and fainting ſpirits, that though we be whipped for extraordinary ſinnes and rebellions with ſharp rods, even as it were of wire and knotted cords, not with ordinary willowes and birches, as in former times, that yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a whipping Father is a Father, and purpoſes to beſtow his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance upon his crying Child if as penitent as peccant: he takes not a ſword to run him through, nor a Dagge to piſtoll him when he is proſtrate on his knees imploring mercy, like the Goſpells relenting prodigall, with a mouth of confeſſion and teares of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, extracted by the heat and fire of love from the Limbeck<note n="a" place="margin">Few fathers prove Tyrants to their owne children, like the Romane <hi>Manlius,</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> or as once <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was before his converſion, and the Jewiſh <hi>Saul</hi> to his <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> whom he would have executed.</note> of a heart full of compunction, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.17, 18, 19. Oh <hi>pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulum ſupplicii ſatis est patri,</hi> a little puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is enough for a father, as we may ſee in the paſſages betwixt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> 2 Sam. 14.21. &amp; cap. 18.33. the beſt Father and the worſt child: all the water of the Sea will not waſh away the love of a Father, it is as ſtrong as death, even when he frownes outwardly, he favours inwardly, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did his Brethren, when he ſpoke roughly to them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.6. <hi>aequa tamen ſemper mens eſt &amp; amica voluntas:</hi> Oh ſuck this refreſhing hony, as a ſecond <hi>Jonathan,</hi> in thy faintings in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of thy woes, that though the evill of ſin this <hi>malum culpae</hi> be from Satan and thy ſelfe, yet this <hi>malum paenae,</hi> the evill of puniſhment is from God, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. &amp; cap. 2.4. <hi>per totum,</hi> puniſhment doe I call it? I thinke I muſt recant the phraſe, for though we read of the plagues of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> of <hi>Sodome,</hi> of <hi>Moab,</hi> of <hi>Edom,</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> of <hi>Gaza,</hi> of <hi>Teman,</hi> of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and of <hi>Tire, Amos</hi> 1. <hi>per totum,</hi> yet Divines diſlike the phraſe of puniſhment ever to be inflicted on the Church of God, or any living members of the Church, the puniſhment of the ſins of all believers being already and at all times laid upon Chriſt the true <hi>Atlas</hi> who hath borne the burthen of his Fathers wrath, paid the ranſome of his brethren, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all their debts, cancelled all their bonds, and given them their <hi>quietut eſt</hi> and Acquittance out of the Chancery or Exchequer of mercy, though they were cleane caſt by <hi>Moſes</hi> and his infringed Law at the Kings Bench of Juſtice, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.4, 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. v. 19, 20, 24, 25. cap. 5.1. &amp; <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. <hi>per totum,</hi> and in this reſpect it being unjuſt with the Judge of heaven and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116244:6"/>earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. to do ought but right, in craving a debt twice to be paid by the principall, when it is paid by the ſuerty, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 1.9. the ſoule married and eſpouſed to Chriſt by faith, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. being now as under covert Baron, not liable to the debts and the arreſts of her widdow-hood, when ſhe was eſtranged from Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. Chriſt her husband being liable unto them, who hath ſatisfied and paid them by his blood, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. even <hi>eo nomine</hi> in this very caſe, the child of God being freed both from the guilt and puniſhment of his ſinne in life, and death, and judgement, whatever happens to him, being not in the nature of a puniſhment from a ſterne <hi>Aeacus, Minos, Radamanthus,</hi> or an <hi>Orbilius Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellator,</hi> or a <hi>Dioniſius in ſchola,</hi> a ſevere Tyrant, an inraged Schoolemaſter, but a caſtigation from a Father, <hi>non quod odio habet ſed quod amat,</hi> not out of hatred, but out of love, what a motive is this to drinke patiently, as Chriſt his Maſter before him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39. and <hi>Job. Iob.</hi> 5.11. and <hi>Ezekias, Eſa.</hi> 39.8. and <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 39.9. and old <hi>Eli,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. and all the Martyrs <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. v. 10. and Confeſſors, the Phyſicall cup his Father hath prepared for him, though very bitter, in the divine providence ſo much the better; if another man equall to thy ſelfe, or inferiour, yea if ſuperiour, hit thee a blow on thy eare, or ſpurn thee with his foot, perhaps thou art moved, and waſpiſh, even a <hi>Micah</hi> or a <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, ſuffering <hi>humani aliquid,</hi> ſome reluctance, to be unjuſtly beaten by a <hi>Zedekias,</hi> a falſe Prophet, a Prelaticall <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> a painted wall, 1 King. 22.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.2, 3. or to be ſcourged unjuſtly by a Governour, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. v. 25. but put the caſe that thy King, thy Leige So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, or thy naturall and affectionate Father give thee a blow or two, (chiefliy upon thy demerits) wilt thou grudge? wilt thou grumble like a curſt Cur? whilſt thou as a whipped dog fly in thy Fathers face? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this caſe of muttering, murmuring, impatiency, like the carnall Iſraelites, againſt God, againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt <hi>Aaron, Exod.</hi> 16.2, 3. cap. 17.2. <hi>Num.</hi> 21.5. in every croſſe and loſſe that hath befallen thee in thy paſt or preſent preſſures, thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe not a mournfull dove, but a hiſſing Snake, yea a ſtinging Serpent, not a patient plundered ſheep, but a gruntling Hog, a tusk-whetting Bore, when the hand of heaven toucheth thee, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if Satan enter ſo farre into thee, as he did into <hi>Iudas, Ioh.</hi> 13.27. and into <hi>Ananias, Act.</hi> 5.3. and into <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. and into <hi>Edens</hi> Serpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1. and into the Pithoniſt or Ventriloquiſt at Philippos, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16. as ſtill he ſpeaks in ſeducing Friers and Jeſuites, in blaſpheming Hereticks, and in all curſing and accurſed ſwearers, that inſtead of bleſſing God in thy croſſes, in thy loſſes by the plundering Caldeans, or Papall Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as <hi>Iob</hi> bleſt God in his greateſt exigents, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.20, 21. thou rave and rage like a Bedlam, ſet thy mouth againſt heaven, like <hi>Homers</hi> Centaures to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116244:6"/>ſight with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> curſe thy Creator, in the devilliſh Dialect of <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, blaſpheme thy Redeemer in tearing againe, worſe then the Jewes on the Croſſe his heart, wounds, bloud, as a Dog doth a harmeleſſe Hare, and a Wolfe an innocent Lambe. In this caſe thou haſt a ſoule as blacke as pitch, ſtinking and ſulphurious. I ſay of thee, as <hi>Simon Peter</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simon Magus, Act.</hi> 8.23. thou art in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquitie, in the very ſnare of the Devill, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. yea his ſympathizing ſonne, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.34. he blaſpheming God in hell, or in the aire where ere he carries his hell about him, and thou on earth, like a Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a French-man, a Spaniard, or an Italian, thou may be known by thy Tongue, to what Countrey thou belongeſt, even to the lower and infernall Regions, to the reall <hi>Styx, Tartaerus,</hi> and <hi>Flegeton,</hi> thy very ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayes thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.37. were Satan on earth, in the forme of a man, or <hi>Caine, Iudas, Achitophel, Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, <hi>Porphiry, Libanius, Hacket, Kett, Michael, Servetus, Dioſcorus, Neſtorius, Arrius,</hi> here againe returned out of hell, they would bring their hell-fired tongues with them, and blaſpheme juſt as thou blaſphemeſt, they would be (as birds of a feather) fit companions and comrades with all God-dam-mees, and Roarers, whoſe mouthes like Butchers dogs, are bloudy with bloudy oathes, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezabel, Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> the Atheiſt and the Papiſt, the Caldean and the Sabaean never agreed better now or heretofore in any miſchiefe plotted or performed, then thou, both in thy mouth and in thy minde, would conſort with ſuch Sathanicall ſympathizers with thy helliſh humours: Oh this courſe, this carriage, is not to kiſſe thy Fathers rod, like a dutifull, a patient, a penitent, a ſubmiſſive Child, but to ſnuffe up the wind like an Onager or wild Aſſe, yea to kick and ſpurn (like <hi>Ieſurum,</hi> Deu. 32.15.) with the heel, as a Mule, when God would catch thee, as we catch wild Colts, in a ſtrait, in a lane, or betwixt thorny hedges, as <hi>Iudah</hi> catched <hi>Adonizebek, Iudg.</hi> 1.4. and the Aſſyrians <hi>Manaſſes</hi> amongſt the thornes, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.11. this ſhewes thou art (as M. <hi>Deering</hi> once uſed the phraſe at the Court) not <hi>tanquam ovis,</hi> as a ſheep ſilent before the ſhearer, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.7. who never bleats when the Butchers knife is at the throat, but <hi>indomita juvenca,</hi> an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed Bullock, bellowing when <hi>Sauls Doegs</hi> or Dogs be about thine eares: I tell thee <hi>Siboleth</hi> and <hi>Shiboleth</hi> did not more clearely diſtinguiſh an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraimite from a Gileadite, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12.6, 7. or the fire doth not more diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh gold from droſſe, or the touch-ſtone gold and pure ſilver from coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit and adulterate metalls, then patience and impatiency, bleſſing or blaſpheming, the language of Canaan and the language of <hi>Aſhdod;</hi> ſhew thy heart (thy mouths fountaine) to be carnall or ſpirituall, degenerate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116244:7"/>or regenerate, the habitation of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17, or a den of Devills, a cage of Scorpions and a neſt of uncleane Birds, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. yea, I ſay, the blew ſpots nor the Carbuncle broke out, doe not more ſhew the plague, nor the white ſpots the Leproſie of a <hi>Gehezi,</hi> a <hi>Miriam,</hi> a <hi>Naaman,</hi> nor a ſtinking breath demonſtrates not more infected lungs, nor the red ploukes and rubies in the face and noſe of a Drunkard, teſtifie not more plainely a too much heated and inflamed Liver, then oaths, curſes, and blaſphemies demonſtrate a rotten, an ulcerous, a poiſoned and a pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heart.</p>
            <p>Oh, looke to it! thou ſaiſt it is thy nature, to curſe, and ſweare, and tear when thou art abaſed, abuſed, wronged or exaſperated, thou art of a hot and cholerick diſpoſition (ſo indeed are all Serpents which make them by a kind of Antipathie with the moiſture of the ſoils, to die as ſoon as ever they are brought into the Iſlands of Gaulon in Creet, or into the Northerne Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponia, or to Ebuſus, or Sardinia,<note n="a" place="margin">Apud Aelianum lib. <hi>5.</hi> Hiſt. c. <hi>2</hi> cum Solino, cap. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi> &amp; Mela, lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> as well as they died in Ireland, for the ſame cauſe, ere ever S. <hi>Patrick</hi> was born) then, thou hot ſpawne of the old Serpent know this, that in this plea of nature, thou ſheweſt there is in thee little grace, rectifying, ruling, conquering, curbing, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying nature, with all naturall luſts, affections and infections, Gal. 5.24. alas! if there be in thee nought but uncleane and polluted nature by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, without regeneration by grace, in thee new birth, the true birth, thou ſhalt (dying in that polluted eſtate) come to heaven, when the Devill and the damned come out of hell, Joh. 3.6. 1 Cor. 15.50. Rev. 21.8. &amp; 27.</p>
            <p>Beſides to bruſh downe the Cobweb lawnes of this excuſe, and to ſhew thee the weakneſſe of this poore paper cloake, to keep off the ſhowers and the ſtormes of deſerved vengeance, may not a Dog as well as thou plead, it is his nature to bark, to bite at ſtrangers, to worry ſheep; the Wolfe, (yea the Iriſh Wolfe called Rebell) that it is his nature to devoure our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Lambs? the Hog, that it's his nature to gruntle, to deſpiſe Pearles? the Aſſe to bray? the Lion to roare? the Horſe-leach to ſuck bloud like a biting Uſurer? the Scarabean Flea, like a Lecher, to delight in filth and dunghills? the drunken Ape and the Monkey to deſire ſtrong liquids? the ſilent Serpent <hi>Dipſas,</hi> like the poyſoning whiſperer and caluminator, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſting? the Turky-cock like an open railer, to bluſter? the houſe Cur like a dogged detracter to bite at the beſt, if they feed him not with cruſts? the Parrot, like a trencher Paraſite and a Buffon, to prate for an Almond? the Swan and the Peacock like a fautaſtick to be proud of their plumes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116244:7"/>without ever looking at their foule and black feet? and ſo the reſt of beaſts ſympathizing with graceleſſe men, in name, natures, and nurtures, 2 Pet. 2.12. Tit. 1.12. may plead nature for their worſt properties moſt prejudiciall unto man, as well as naturall men for their belluine and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing conditions, poetized by <hi>Ovid</hi> to be turned into beaſts. But let me expoſtulate with thee a little further, what getteſt thou by thy impatient imprecations or execrations? (which thou mayeſt as well ſpare as dirt from thy nailes, or ſmoke from thy chimney) they gaine thee not ſo much as a ſhooe latchet; nay, (like jealouſie and gnawing envy) they are their owne plagues, cauſeleſſe curſes like balls throwne up into the aire, light pat on thine owne pate; thou hurteſt none by them but thy ſelfe, like ſquibs they flaſh and crack, and ſend their ſtink in thy owne noſe: the ball thrown againſt a wall hurts not the wall, no more then the waves which daſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rock hurt the rock, but breake themſelves to froath and foame: in raging againſt God or man thou kickeſt againſt an Iron prick, and the Iron enters into thy owne ſoule, Acts 9.6. thou roaſts at thy owne fire, and hurts thy fretting furious ſelfe: beſides impatiency in a croſſe cures it, as mire and ſoot waſh thy face fowler and fowler, what is it but as Mercury to a green wound more to fret it? yea, as the horſe in a quagmire, a bird in the limebuſh, and the rabbet in the Warreners net; the more the impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient madcap ſtrives and ſtruggles, the more he intangles himſelfe; if he belongs unto God, he will make him quiet for all his plunging: if he be his Child by adoption, he will uſe more rods, and lay them on more ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but he will ere he have done with him, make him as calme as a Lambe, and as meek as a Dove: when Gods winds of wrath begin to blow and bluſter againſt any ſoule, he will either make it bow by humiliation, like a yeelding reed, as did <hi>David,</hi> Pſa. 6.5, 6. <hi>Ezekias,</hi> 2 Chron. 32.24, 25, 26. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> 2 Chron. 33.11, 12. and oft repenring Iſrael, Judg. 2.5.6.7. 1 Sam. 7.6.7. Judg. 3.9. or he will blow it downe as a ſterne and ſtubborne Oake, by an utter rooting out and ſubverſion, as he did <hi>Pharoah,</hi> Exod. 14.27. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab,</hi> 1 King. 22. <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and <hi>Jeconiah,</hi> buried (like many now) with the buriall of an Aſſe, with millions more in all ages, 1 King. 3, 34.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I ſay unto thee, in thy curſes and execrations againſt this Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and that Round-head, in City, Court, or Camp, or ſound head, as our turbulent times have made the unhappy diſtinctions, as once betwixt the Guelphs and Gibellines in Italy, betwixt the Aurelians and Burgundians in France, and betwixt the Lancaſtrians, and thoſe of the houſe of Yorke in England; as once God ſaid to <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> and <hi>Senecharib,</hi> whom haſt thou reproached and blaſphemed? and againſt whom haſt thou exalted thy voice, even againſt the holy one of Iſrael, 2 King. 19.21. againſt whom
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116244:8"/>doſt thou caſt thy ſquibs and darts and fire-brands? againſt whom (like an Armenian Dragon) doſt thou ſpit fire? thou ſaieſt againſt man, a weake worme like thy ſelf, I tell thee, nay, it is againſt God, as I have before made it plaine, who now hath ſet man againſt thee, as his rod to whip to ſcourge thee, as he calls the King of Aſhur, his rod againſt Iſrael, even the rod of his anger in the hand of his indignation, Iſai. 10.5. as <hi>Attilas</hi> the cruell Goth, called himſelfe <hi>Flagellum Dei,</hi> the whip of God to ſcourge the world, as <hi>Tamberlane</hi> was but Gods rod againſt <hi>Bajazet:</hi> the Turke, and as the Turk in his conqueſts of Cyprus, Rhodes, Famaguſta, Conſtantinople, Malta, and in his inroads ſtill into Hungary, Tranſilvania, Dalmatia, Cracovia, and lately into ſome Sea coaſts in Ireland, hath been and ſtill is Gods rod and ſcourge to Idolatrous, Adulterous, bloudy, cruell, extorting, proud, drunken, prophane, and hypocriticall Chriſtendome, to apoſtatizing Europaeans from their firſt faith, as well as the Romans now in ſome points, and as the Mahumetanized Churches of Aſia, once planted by the Apoſtles: ſo what are the Imperialiſts and Auſtrians now, but the rod of angry <hi>Nemeſis</hi> againſt Germany, and the Palatinate for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel, chiefly for their overſpreading painted Popery called Arminianiſme, and ſo what is the confederacy now of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> our Hibernified Atheiſts, Papiſts, Carnalliſts, with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Caniballs, ſpoiling the goods and ſucking the blouds of many true-hearted <hi>Naboths</hi> and <hi>Nathanaels:</hi> what are theſe but Gods rods up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to correct our long forborne Delinquencies now viſited in Gods great Audit or Correction day, Jer. 9.6, 10. yea one of us fighting againſt another of the ſame Religion and Profeſſion, as many heads of the Serpent <hi>Amphiſbena</hi> are ſaid to fight one with another, as we lately (like the Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites in Gideons time, Judg. 7.22. againſt the Midianites, the Ammonites, and Moabites in <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> time, againſt the Syrians, 2 Chron. 20.23. as the ſervants of <hi>Abner</hi> and of <hi>Ioab</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> time, 2 Sam. 2.15, 16.) ſheathing our ſwords in the bowells one of another, as it is writ of <hi>Cadmus</hi> his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and of <hi>Brennus</hi> and <hi>Brentius, Polinices</hi> and <hi>Eteocles, Romulus</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> one of us deſtroying another, like Bees in a Hive, in a bloudy faction, not Bees againſt Church-Drones, and State-Catterpillers at home, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Romiſh Waſps and Aſps at home and abroad; what are theſe but rods in Gods hand, by which in his juſt &amp; unſearchable juſtice, he makes us to whip and ſcourge one another more bloodily then the Iewes once ſcourged S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.14. or then the Monks of <hi>Bangor</hi> whipped once poore King <hi>Iohn;</hi> the reſult of all is, when any man is an inſtrument to doe us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good, as <hi>Obadiah</hi> to a hundred poor Prophets, 1 King. 18.13. and <hi>David</hi> to lame <hi>Mephiboſeth,</hi> 2 Sam. 9. and the good Ethiopian <hi>Ebedmelech</hi> to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116244:8"/>
               <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Ier. 38.7, 8. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> to the noble <hi>Eunuch,</hi> Act. 8.36.37. ſuch a man is unto us a rod of beauty in Gods right hand, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.10. when any doth unto us any damage and detriment, either in plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our goods, as Caldeans to <hi>Job</hi> 1.17. or ſhedding our bloods, as <hi>Caine</hi> did <hi>Abells,</hi> Gen. 4. or impriſoning our bodies, as the Philippian Magiſtrates did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> Act. 16. or ſmiting us, as <hi>Paſhur</hi> the Prelate did <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy,</hi> Jer. 20.2. or doing us much evill, as <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper-ſmith did <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.14. in theſe caſes and the like, man is unto us (as he is called in <hi>Zachary,</hi>) a rod of hands in Gods hands, yea how ever man is to man, <hi>homo homini Deus, aut demon aut lupus,</hi> a God, a Devill, or a Wolfe, though in ſheeps cloathing, whether a <hi>Jonathan,</hi> a <hi>Ioab,</hi> or a <hi>Iudas,</hi> he is but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of God to plague man, or to pleaſure man, God himſelfe ſetting even Kings themſelves over men good or bad in juſtice or mercy for his owne ſecret ends; the ſame God (if we believe S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) who gave <hi>Auguſtus Trajan, Adrian,</hi> and good Emperours, Fathers of their Countries, giving alſo <hi>Nero, Caligula, Decius, Domitian,</hi> and other truculent Tyrants: <hi>David</hi> was ſo ſenſible of this truth, that when <hi>Shemei</hi> reviled him, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to God the ſetting this Bandog upon him, 2 Sam. 6.10. ſo <hi>Job</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes his plunderings not to the Sabeans, the inſtruments, but to Gods permiſſive providence, giving and taking Goods from him, Job 1.21. and <hi>Joſeph</hi> aſcribes his ſelling and ſending into Egypt not ſo much to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as to God himſelfe, Gen 45. v. 5. yea whatſoever <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the Jewe and the Gentiles, and <hi>Judas</hi> did to Chriſt in his crucifying, the Apoſtles attribute it to the Counſell and Decree of God, Act. 4.26, 27. <hi>Judas</hi> acting in the death of Chriſt out of covetouſneſſe, Luk. 22.5. the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees out of envy, Mar. 15.10. <hi>Pilate</hi> out of baſe and ſervile feare to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Jewes, Mar. 15. v. 15. but God wrought in all theſe permiſſively and diſpoſitively, to the glory of his mercy and juſtice, to the redemption of his elected one, Col. 1.14. the obduration of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, the riſing and falling of many in Iſrael, Luk. 2.34. as I have reflexed fully on this point in my <hi>Origens</hi> repentance.</p>
            <p>Theſe premiſes conſidered, thou never looking up to God in thy preſent loſſes, croſſes, preſſures, plunderings, the chiefe efficient cauſe, Iam. 3.38. not to thy owne unrepented ſinnus, the meritorious and deſerving cauſe, 1 Sam. 12.18.19. Iam. 3.39. but meerly unto man the inſtrumentall cauſe, like a Swine, who hath eyes onely to look downeward to the earth, but never upwards to heaven, looking upon the creature with the eyes of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reaſon, without the Creator, thou art inraged againſt this man and that man, thy heart riſeth at him, as at an Incendiary object, as Turky-cocks and Unicornes be inraged at the ſight of red Stammell, and as Bullocks
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116244:9"/>bellow at the ſent or ſight of blood; hence thou goareſt thy enemy in the ſides, thou teareſt him with thy tongue, as a chaſed Horſe or Boare, thou caſts thy ſcums and froths upon him, and art as much exaſperated againſt him, as the Romanes againſt <hi>Caſſius, Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Dolobella,</hi> when they ſaw the bloudy garments of ſtabbed <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe mad poſtures of thine acting the parts of a ſecond mad <hi>Ajax</hi> againſt <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> or of <hi>Hercules, Furens,</hi> or <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> in the Tragedians, againſt meer man, never looking up to God nor into thy ſelfe; what doſt thou but like a teſty dog which runs after a ſtone throwne at him, which he bites and ſnarles, never looking at the hand that throwes it, as if a foole ſhould breake an arrow all to fitters which hits him and hurts him, wreaking his wrath on it (as the fabled Weazle to her owne burning, bit the hot yron which fell upon her foot) never looking to the arme which drew the bow and ſhot it; as ſome graceleſſe Fellons and their friends as I have ſeen, throw ſtones at the Hang-man and curſe the Executioner, never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that it is the Judge, the Law, and their owne demerits and fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which execute them, the poore hang-man doth but his office: thou in this caſe that rageſt againſt thy foes, thy formall friends, plunderers, yea, againſt Committees, Excize men, Sequeſtrators and the like, licking their owne fingers, and feathering thou thinkeſt their own wings, (ſome of them as receivers, deceivers have been, yea, Empſonians, Dudleans, Zacheuſſes, and Publicans have ſitten at the receit or deceit of cuſtome, cuſtomarily in all ages;) thou art poſſeſſed with ſuch a mad and malignant, ſpirit as whiſome that great hearted <hi>Byron</hi> in France, and <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Arch-Traitor in England who in their impatiency breathing revenge, even in death would have wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their wraths on their very Executioners, whom our once noble <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawely,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> and the late Hibernian Heroes as freely forgave, as S. <hi>Stephen</hi> did his ſtoners, Act. 7.60. Chriſt and his primitive and moderne Martyrs, their Crucifiers, Luke 23.34. <hi>vade &amp; tu fac ſimiliter,</hi> doe thou the like according to Chriſts practice and precept, Mat. 5.44. if thou willeſt be a patrizing ſympathizing ſon of a heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>And to ſet a further edge upon thee to the performance of this dutie and to curb and bridle thy corrupt heart, which is ever meditating mould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, plotting, ſearching and projecting revenge againſt thoſe that have made thee extreamly paſſive in plucking thy golden feathers, and making thee as naked as a worme, or as <hi>Eſops</hi> Crow, when ſhe was deplumed, nothing (according to Machiavells rule and the Italians practice) being ſweeter then revenge, to give a <hi>Rowland</hi> for an <hi>Oliver,</hi> to pay an enemy home in his own coine in retalinted vengeance, an eye for an eye, even as one mad dog or wolfe devoures another; but chiefly ſince this forgiving and forgetting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116244:9"/>injuries as the Eſtridge forgets her egges, writing wrongs in duſt, is <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſermo,</hi> a bitter pill to ſwallow a hard morſell to digeſt, going againſt the haire, againſt the heart, againſt the very ſtreame and torrent of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, againſt the courſe and cuſtome of the world and worldlings, ſince <hi>hoc opus hic labor,</hi> to ſubdue thy rebellious nature, and conquer thy corrupt heart in this caſe is more then an Herculean taske, a greater Conqueſt then to ſubdue a <hi>Cacus,</hi> a <hi>Cerberus,</hi> an <hi>Hidra,</hi> a <hi>Leana,</hi> a Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian Boare, with <hi>Meleager,</hi> or a Serpent at Bagrada, with <hi>Regulus:</hi> therefore to help thee in this conqueſt; this one conſideration may be as valiant a Champion for thee as <hi>Achilles</hi> for his <hi>Patroclus,</hi> namely, that thoſe againſt whom thy heart ſo riſeth and rageth, are not thy enemies, and then with whom ſighteſt thou thus, but with thine owne ſhadow? or as a <hi>Don Quixot</hi> with Rams and Windmills? but at this thou ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt as <hi>Moſes</hi> at his rod turned Serpent, Exod. 4.2. and crieſt out, as once <hi>Michay</hi> and <hi>Laban,</hi> Gen. 31.30. they have ſtollen away my Gods, Judg. 10.24. my goods, my golden Calfe which I adored. Col. 3.5. and are they not mine enemies? but <hi>bona verbil quaeſo,</hi> be not ſo haſty, <hi>feſtina lentè,</hi> pawſe a little upon it, and thou wilt find that if thou couldſt but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the rule of <hi>Plutarch</hi> a Pagan, how to make uſe of enemies, and to get fruits from foes, even grapes of grace from the thornes and thiſtles of their hoſtility, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> got hony even out of a dead Lion, Judg. 14.8. then thou wouldeſt ſee, that as <hi>Iſaac</hi> miſtook <hi>Jacob</hi> for <hi>Eſau,</hi> Gen. 27.24. ſo thou haſt all this while miſtook thy friends for thy foes; and as one cried in Stobeus, <hi>O philoioudè philoi,</hi> O friends, no friends, ſo thou ſhouldſt cry, O foes no foes; or if foes in the effects of your Vatinian hate, yet in the effect you are no foes, as you better mine eſtate, as you are fierce winds to drive my ſin-fraught ſoule to the haven of grace, to the port of peace, as you are like gall and ſoot laid to the deſired duggs of the bewitching world, to weane me from it, as Surgeons with ſharp Goads to Phlebotomize my vaine veines, to cure me in the dangerous Pluriſies and burning Feavers of my boiling luſts, to prick and breake (though with your ſwords and rapiers) the ſecret Impoſtimes of my pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid hypocriſie, my ſordid covetouſneſſe, with the ſwelling tympany of my pride, and vaine glory, getting thus good from the intended harms of thy foes, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mardocheus</hi> were brought to exaltation by a envious oppoſition, <hi>Daniel</hi> to further grace with <hi>Darius,</hi> and his three companions to higher places by calumination, and detraction, Gen. 40.38. Eſther 7. Dan. c. 3. cap. 6. which was alſo the caſe of <hi>Herod</hi> at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Auguſius Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> and of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> in Athens, exiled to his advancement: I ſay if thou get ſweet ſiggs of grace from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116244:10"/>and wormwood of thy enemies, as Phyſitians and Paracelſians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Antidotes and Mithridate againſt poiſons, and Reſtoratives againſt Conſumptions, even from poiſonous Toads, Nutes and Serpents, then thy ſuppoſed foes are but men made of ſtrawes, but Scar-Crowes in Cherry Trees; thou fighteſt but with ſhadowes, as ſome Hiperboreans are ſaid to fight with the North wind, and Pigmees with Cranes, thou art more frighted then hurt with theſe Eutopians, as children with Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares, who onely (like the Apes in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who marched with green boughs in their Clawes on the ſide of a mountaine) ſeem to be enemies, but are not, or at moſt enemies in their acts, but friends in their effects, as the divine providence diſpoſeth of their evill wills to effect in thee his owne good worke, as their deep furrowes plowed in thy humbled and rent heart, fits it by receiving the ſeed of the Word, the Goſpell of grace to bring forth the harveſt of ſanctified fruits more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with patience, which being the very marke I ſhoot at, and the naile I drive at, that the City may be anſwerable to the gate, this Tractate to the Title of Fruits from Foes, let me but hammer into thy head and heart theſe ſubſequent conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that if thou be a foe to thine owne luſts, which fight againſt thy ſoule, 1 Pet. 2.11. and hateſt meerly what God hates, ſin in thy ſelfe and others, as did <hi>David,</hi> Pſa. 119.115. and <hi>Lot,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.7. and <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Jer. 9.1. it is an evident argument to thy own ſoule, that as was ſaid of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Jam. 2.17. of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> John 11.11. and Chriſts Diſciples, John 15.11. thou art Gods friend, and therefore no marvell if the world be thy foe; for if thou wert of the world, the world would love his owne, John 15.19. as every Ape her owne young, every Crow and Owle her owne Bird, every Ethiopian Mother her owne Child, though as black as her ſelfe, as <hi>cicada cicadae chara, &amp; Graculus aſſidet Graculo,</hi> one Jay jangles to another, and birds of a feather flock together; <hi>Ego novi Sino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; Sinon novit me,</hi> as <hi>Eraſmuus</hi> hath it in his adage, a couple of Knaves are as well met, as the biting uſurer and his broker, the thiefe and the refetter, the braggadochean <hi>Thraſo</hi> and his trencher Paraſite <hi>Gnato,</hi> and as a luxurious Prince and a <hi>Gaveſton</hi> his fatall Pander, a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Prince that like a Hawke would pounce golden game, loves ſuch Officers as are Spaniels to ſpring it, and a drowſie, dull, dead hearted people, love ſuch a Paſtor as will charme them aſleep in their Lethargi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſecurity, and ſow pillowes under their elbowes, to further their ſlumbering in the ſhadow of death, but a <hi>Boanerges,</hi> a ſonne of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that will ſound in their eares <hi>Eſayes</hi> Trump, and ring <hi>Aarons</hi> Bells, and cry with the voice of a Baptiſt to awaken them ere the Trump of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116244:10"/>Judgement, 1 Theſ. 4.16. he is no Lettice for their lips, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, Act. 22.22. <hi>ſimilis ſimili gaudet,</hi> like loves his like, by a naturall ſympathie and ſimilitude, <hi>cauſa amoris,</hi> ſimilitude drawes love as the adamant the iron, and the Caeſian winds the clouds, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimilitude breeds diſlike and diſtaſte in judgement and affection: Hence if thou beeſt in Chriſt, and crucified to the world and the world to thee, Gal. 2.20. &amp; cap. 5.24. there is as great an Antipathie betwixt thy enemy and Chriſts enemy, and the worlds friend and favourite that is meerly carnall, 1 Cor. 3.3. Jam. 4.4. 1 Joh. 2.15. and thou that art ſpirituall, 1 Cor. 2.15. and truly anſwereſt thy name Chriſtian, Acts 15.26. as there is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement betwixt grace and nature, light and darkneſſe, God and Mammon, Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.15, 16. <hi>Michael</hi> and the Dragon, Rev. 12.7. yea as there is contrariety betwixt the Elephant and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne, the Fox and the Lamb, and the Wolfe and the Sheep, whoſe very guts made into ſtrings will never accord and tune together in a Lute, more then the bloods of <hi>Polinices</hi> and <hi>Eteocles</hi> would mix together after they had ſlaine each other: aſſure thy ſelfe, let a carnall man, either an open prophane wretch like <hi>Eſau,</hi> or a rotten hearted hypocrite ſyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantize with thee and obſerve thee for his owne ſiniſter ends, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto thee as <hi>Demas</hi> once to <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. yet ſo long as thy works are good and his evill, and thy life and light a reall Sermon to blame and ſhame his, he loves thee no better then <hi>Judas</hi> did Chriſt whom he betrayed, then <hi>Herod</hi> did the Baptiſt whom he beheaded, though he reverenced and heard him gladly, Mar. 6.20. nay he hates thee inwardly for the ſame cauſe that <hi>Caine</hi> hated <hi>Abel,</hi> 1 John 3.12. <hi>Jezabel Elias,</hi> 1 King. 19.2. and <hi>Ahab Micaiah,</hi> becauſe he propheſied no good unto him, 1 King. 22.8. becauſe thy right ſteered life, like <hi>Noahs</hi> once amongſt the worldings, and <hi>Lots</hi> among the Sodomites, Luk. 17.27, 28. ſhames the irregularities of their vaine diſcourſes and vitious courſes, <hi>Lux oculis aegris odioſa,</hi> thy light which ſhines before men, Mat. 5.16. offends their blood-ſhotten eyes, as the Sun doth the pur-blind Owle, the Lion, Wolfe, Fox, Badger, Otter, Fowmant, Weazill, Poulecat, and all beaſts of prey, love the night better then the day, darkneſſe more then light: now thou art of the day, if Chriſt the Day-ſtar be riſen in thy heart, Luk. 1.78. and ſhine in that Orb by faith, Eph. 3.17. thy enemies are of the night, 1 Theſ. 5.4, 5. therefore however they ſeem to collogue and to cloſe with thee, they are as diſcrepant from thee in their diſpoſitions, and at as farre a diſtance in their infected affections, as the Northern and Southern Pole; the Raven is thought by ſome to forſake her young ones for a time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in their firſt hatching they are white and downy, then God is ſaid
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116244:11"/>to feed them; but after a while when ſhe returnes and finds them black like her ſelfe, ſhe takes to them as her owne, <hi>fabula de te narratur, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corius</hi> in his Morall Reductory, and <hi>Geminianus</hi> in his Similies make the Application.</p>
            <p>Now is this no fruit from a Foe, that his hoſtility proclaimes thee to be Chriſts friend? whoſe love will ſtand thee in a thouſand times more ſtead then <hi>Ionathans</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>Damons</hi> to his <hi>Pithias:</hi> A wiſe Courtier had rather have his King his friend, with his <hi>Ego &amp; Rex meus,</hi> though all the emulating Court be againſt him, then to curry favour with the Court, and be at a frowning diſtance with the King, <hi>ſi Deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos?</hi> if God be with thee, who can be againſt thee? Rom. 8.31. if I have the Sun ſhining in my face, what need I the leſſer twinkling Starres, or the light of a candle which may go out with the leaſt windy puffe, and leave in my noſe a ſtinking ſnuffe? it's ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be aſſured I am in the right way in my Pilgrimage to my heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly home, though all the Dogs (and <hi>Doegs</hi>) barke at me in every Town thorough which I paſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as a Corollary to this conſider ſeriouſly, that if thou be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, <hi>ſuſtinendo &amp; abſtinendo,</hi> in which <hi>Epictetus</hi> epitomized Morall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, in ſuſtaining and bearing the brunts and blaſts of thy foes, and in abſtaining and forbearing from revenge, then God is ingaged by promiſe, which he ever performes, 1 Theſ. 5.23. to be thy avenger on thy enemies if in thee they oppoſe him, Rom. 12.19. as he avenged <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Michals</hi> mocks, 2 Sam. 6.16.20.23. of <hi>Shimeies</hi> revilings, 2 Sam. 16.10. 1 King. 2.44. of <hi>Nabals</hi> churliſhneſſe, 1 Sam. 25.39. <hi>Ezaekiah</hi> of the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> and the blaſphemies of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> 2 King. 19.28.37. <hi>Abraham</hi> of the intended wrongs of <hi>Abimelech,</hi> Gen. 20.7.18. a zealous Prophet on <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> whoſe hand he withered, 1 King. 13.4. <hi>Moſes</hi> on <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> whom the earth ſwallowed, Numb. 16. <hi>Lot</hi> on the Sodomites whom he firſt blinded, Gen. 19.11. and then burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, V. 24. as he did <hi>Valens</hi> the Arrian in a Shepheards Cottage, the great enemy to S. <hi>Baſil,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Apud Marcell. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Hiſt.</note> ſo he avenged the Counſell of Calcedon on their grand enemy <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> whom he ſmit with a Thunderbolt, <hi>Eutropius,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 5. <hi>Azariah</hi> the high Prieſt, on preſumptuous <hi>Vzziah,</hi> whom he ſmit with Leproſie, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.20, 21. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> on <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Arrian Emperour, whom hee cut off in great diſtraction of mind,<note place="margin">Idem Hiſt. lib. <hi>12.</hi> Amb. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on <hi>Valentinian</hi> his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who was hanged by his owne ſervants,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116244:11"/>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the beſt Roman Biſhop of thoſe that ſucceeded him, on <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the covetous Emperour ſlain by <hi>Phocas</hi> a cruell coward<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Blondus</hi> lib. 3. decad.</note>, with many more which might be enumerated in all times and ages, the Lord ever ſiding with his Sion, his Militant Church, againſt all her malignant oppoſers, as he did with his Chriſt her Head and Husband againſt <hi>Herod,</hi> the Scribes, the Phariſees, <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas,</hi> chiefly on <hi>Pilate,</hi> who hanged himſelfe after his diſgraces with <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Caius,</hi> as their Tragedies are recorded, not onely by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> Hiſt. lib. 2 c. 7. and <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> lib. 2. c. 10. but even by the Paganiſh Writers of the Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of the Greeks.</p>
            <p>Now is this no fruit from a foe, that as his wrongfull, undeſerved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provoked hatred and oppoſition ſhewes thee (as I have proved) to be Chriſts friend, ſo reciprocally Chriſt to be thy friend: as <hi>Pilades</hi> was to <hi>Orestes,</hi> as well as <hi>Orestes</hi> to <hi>Pila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t praeſtem <hi>Piladem</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis mihi praeſtat <hi>Oreſtem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Niſus</hi> to <hi>Eurialus, Titus</hi> to <hi>Giſippus,</hi> as well as <hi>Eurialus</hi> to <hi>Niſus, Giſippus</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> according to the rule, <hi>ut ameris ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis eſto,</hi> love begetting love, as one candle lights another, one burning coale kindles another, yea, as Naphtha is ſaid to take fire at the neere approach of fire: and is Chriſts friendſhip barren of golden, of gracious fruits? Can a true friend indeed, an <hi>alter ego,</hi> a ſecond ſelfe, a <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphus,</hi> a ſworne brother, a friend and a brother, in the bond of bloud, in the neereſt link of love, as Chriſt is to his Church, Heb. 2.12, 17. ſtand by and ſee his friend need and bleed, yea in the paw of a Wolfe, or a Lion, or in the fangs of a mad Dog, or on the hornes of a Bull of Baſan, and he adminiſter no helpe from a ſtrong and an armed arme? Can a father, though as ſterne as a <hi>Manlius,</hi> or a <hi>Brutiu,</hi> do this to a child, if there be any ſtorge or ſparke of affection in him, if he do not more ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidly then a Stoick or ſtock, <hi>hominem exuere,</hi> put off all that ſpeaks him man, like a brutized monſter? yea, can a Husband doe this that loves his Wife in the neereſt and deareſt union, which <hi>Tullie</hi> himſelfe makes mariage, in his book of friendſhip. Now was there ever any Father lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Child as Chriſt doth all his Children by adoption, who cry <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, Rom. 8.14, 15. Did <hi>Abraham</hi> ever ſo love his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> his ſonne by nature and by promiſe, as Chriſt doth every beleever the ſonne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> by faith, Gal. 3.7. as <hi>Zacheus</hi> was called, Luke 19.10. Was there ever in the beſt improvement of love, ſuch a neer and dear union and communion of morall love, betwixt <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Hiram, Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Neſtor,</hi> Theologicall love, betwixt <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Nazianzene, Auguſtine</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116244:12"/>and <hi>Alipius, Euſebius</hi> and his <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> naturall love betwixt <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph, Helena</hi> and her <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> Matrimoniall love betwixt <hi>Jſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecka, Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Anna, Admetus</hi> and his <hi>Alceſt, Brutus</hi> and his <hi>Portia, Collatinus</hi> and his <hi>Lucrece,</hi> as betwixt Chriſt and his eſpouſed and contracted Church, and every living and loving member of the ſame? Hoſ. 2.19. Eph. 5.23.24.32. now thou art ingrafted into Chriſt as a wild Olive by nature into a good Olive tree, Rom. 11.24. and in him brings forth much fruit, John 15.4, 5. this is one fruit amongſt the reſt which growes on the tree of thy penitence and patience, that if thou ſtand for Chriſt, for his Truth, for his Religion, as once that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> called the <hi>Atlas</hi> of the Faith, he will be ſure to ſtand for thee, and to be with thee as thy Champion, and deliver when thou paſſeſt through the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and through the rivers that they doe not overflow thee, as he was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and Iſrael in the red Sea, Exod. 14. and with <hi>Noah</hi> in the firſt univerſall Deluge, Gen. 7.1. and he will be with thee when thou walkeſt through the fire, as he was with the three Jewiſh Martyrs in the furnace, Dan. 3.25. and with S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the furnace, into which <hi>Domitian</hi> caſt him,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert.</hi> in praeſcrip. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Haeret.</note> according to his promiſe to all true Iſraelites, the ſpirituall ſonnes of <hi>Iacob, Eſay</hi> 43.1, 2, 3. yea he will be with thee as he was with wreſtling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering <hi>Iacob,</hi> Gen. 32.24. when any <hi>Laban</hi> or <hi>Eſau</hi> comes againſt thee for any intended miſchiefe; Oh aſſure thy ſelfe he will be with thee when thou art amongſt Lions, as he was with <hi>Daniel,</hi> cap. 6. and when thou fighteſt with ſuch beaſts as <hi>Paul</hi> fought with at Epheſus, 1 Cor. 15.32. with Beares as <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 17. with young Lions as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> Judg. 15. and with men whoſe tongues are ſwords and ſharp arrowes, and under whoſe lips is the poyſon of Aſps; yea if thy enemies with the horne of their power puſh thee into priſon he is with thee there alſo, as with <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> in <hi>Putiphars</hi> Goale, Gen. 29.21. with <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the dark Dungeon, Jer. 32.2. with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> in the Philippian Priſon, Act. 16.25, 26. yea with pious <hi>Philpot,</hi> once in the Biſhop of Londons Cole-hole, and with that Martyr in Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> his Martyrologie, who writ from his priſon his delectable Paradiſe in Argiers, yea if thou beeſt exiled and baniſhed from thy houſe and harbour, he is with thee where ever thou art racketed and bandied, as he was with <hi>Abraham</hi> in a ſtrange Countrey, Gen. 12.7. with <hi>Iſaac</hi> amongſt the Philiſtines, Gen. 26.12.24. with <hi>Jacob</hi> in Padan-Aram, Gen. 20.43. and in Egypt, Gen. 47.27. yea if thou beeſt led to execution and to ſuffering for his names ſake, to which there is a bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, Mat. 5.12. he is with thee there alſo, as he was with <hi>Peter</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116244:12"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> crucified with their heads downwards, with <hi>Laurence</hi> roaſted on a Gridiron, with <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> grinded to be pure Manchet for Chriſt, with the teeth of Lions, with <hi>Dagilla, Tecla, Quintilia, Petronella,</hi> pulled and torne in their fleſh from the bone with burning Pincers, yea with our Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Martyrs, ſincere <hi>Saunders,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Bradford</hi> joyfully pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his vowes in Smithfield, truſty <hi>Tailor</hi> skipping in joyfull Levaltoes when he was neere his burning ſacrifice, godly <hi>Glover</hi> ſenſible of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Spirit, and with that young man who at the ſtake no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner cryed Sun of God ſhine upon me, but in a dark and gloomy day the Sun caſt ſuch gleames on him on a ſudden, as aſtoniſhed all the Spectators, yea as their laſt foe and enemy that is to be ſubdued is death, 1 Cor. 15.</p>
            <p>Chriſt according to his promiſe, Pſal. 41.3. is with his Saints, they have him with old <hi>Simeon</hi> in the armes of their faith: and with <hi>Paul</hi> live and die by faith; both in their naturall death as he was with <hi>Jacob</hi> bowing and worſhipping on his ſick bed; and with <hi>Theodoſius, Auguſtne, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Luther, Calvin, Oecalampadius</hi> and others, whoſe laſt ſpirituall breathings, with Spirits ſurrendred into their Fathers hands, are recorded to exultation and admiration by <hi>Grineus</hi> in his <hi>Apothegmata morientium,</hi> amongſt his <hi>Theſis in quarto,</hi> as alſo he is with them in the moſt virulent &amp; violent deaths, which cruelty and tiranny can invent; as he was with every one of his Apoſtles, who were martired (excepting S. <hi>John</hi>) whoſe acts, lives and glorious deaths, are fully recorded to any that will for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and imitation peruſe them in <hi>Euſebius</hi> his firſt book of Hiſtories cap. 25. his ſecond book, cap 1. his third book. cap 1. his ninth book cap 1. <hi>Nicephorus</hi> his ſecond book cap. 40. his fourth book cap. 7. <hi>Sabellicus</hi> his ſeventh book Eneid. 4. <hi>Ruſſinus</hi> his firſt book cap. 9. <hi>Hierom</hi> in the life of <hi>Paul,</hi> the Magdeburgians in their Centuries, Cent. 1. lib. 2. cap. 10. and <hi>Hoſiander</hi> their Epitomizer, Cent. 1. lib. 2. cap. 30. which I alledge as Inns by the way, where the learned reader may drink if he will, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned paſſe by them if he like them not.</p>
            <p>The reſult of all is this, if thou be a Believer, (for I have Cordialls onely for ſuch as coraſives to the ſlaves of ſinne and Satan) if thou haſt ſuch relations to Chriſt as I have touched upon, as to a head, a husband a father, a friend, then let who will be the rod in Gods hand to afflict thee, the inſtrument or executioner to torment thee, be they <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels</hi> and <hi>Hamans</hi> for peſtilent plots, <hi>Judaſſes</hi> and <hi>Joabs</hi> for treachery, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, Caligulaes,</hi> and <hi>Perianders,</hi> for cruelty, Serpents for ſubtilty, Lions for power, Foxes for policie, though they ſpin never ſuch Spiders webs to catch thee, ſet never ſo covered ſnares to intrap thee, though they deſpiſe thee, diſpight thee, vilifie thee, nullifie thee, revile thee,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116244:13"/>peeſecute thee, and hunt thee as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> as <hi>Iezabel</hi> did <hi>Elias,</hi> and Pope <hi>Leo Luther,</hi> though they defame thee and ſleight thee, as the falſe Apoſtles did <hi>Paul,</hi> as the Phariſees did Chriſt, as the Arrians the Orthodox Chriſtians, as the Papiſts all Proteſtants, ſome calling their very hounds by the name of <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and the like, as the mad and unwormed whelps of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> our Familiſts, Fantaſticks, new See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and Anabablers, terme now all zealous and judicious Divines no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then black Dogs barking in Pulpits, in Steeple and Stone Churches, as Satan ſpeakes in them as at firſt, ſo ſtill in Serpents: I fay, if they could hate thee, and howle at thee more then <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiry</hi> and <hi>Lucian</hi> the Atheiſt againſt thy incarnate Saviour, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I can give thee this mirth in mourning, joy in tribulation, light in darkneſſe, rejoycing in ſuffering, Act. 5.40. 1 Cor. 4.9, 10. honour in thy diſgrace, 1 Sam. 2.30. and ſuch an <hi>Ariadnees</hi> thred to bring thee out of the mazes and Labyrinths of their perturbations, (as I have given Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialls for every other croſſe in the end of my ſeven helps to Heaven) that thou mayeſt be ſure of a good iſſue in a victorious Trophie and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over all thy enemies, if thou canſt but reſt and rely by faith and affiance on the Lord of Hoſts, who fights in thee, with thee, and for thee, as he fought in and for <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.45. in and for <hi>Ionathan</hi> againſt the Philiſtines, 1 Sam. 14.6. for <hi>Gideon</hi> againſt the Midianites, Judg. 7.20. for <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> againſt the Amorites and Syrians, 2 Chro. 20.12.13. in and for <hi>Abraham</hi> againſt five Kings, Gen. 14.13. in and for <hi>Joſhuah</hi> againſt the Canaanites, Joſ. 1.5. cap. 5.14. in and for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biah</hi> againſt Idolatrous <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 2 Chron. 13.9, 10. in and for <hi>Aſa,</hi> who relyed on him againſt the Lubims and Ethiopians, 2 Chron. 16.8. in and for <hi>Barak</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> againſt <hi>Jabin</hi> and <hi>Siſera,</hi> Judg. 4. yea beſides infallible Scripture inſtances, as he is the ſame God to day, yeſterday and for ever, Heb. 13.8. <hi>ſemper praeſenter hic &amp; ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> potenter,</hi> as the great ſoule of the world, as <hi>Plato</hi> calls him ever preſent and reſident with his Church, Mat. 28.20. ever neer to them who draw neer to him, Jam. 4.8. as a friend to helpe at a dead lift, even in the laſt exigent of extremity, which is uſually his oportunity, even when a red Sea is before his Church, and a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> behind: ſo why can he not, why will he not deliver thee, yea this whole nation according to his promiſe, Jer. 18.4, 5. in his due time, ſince his hand is not ſhortned, Eſay 59.2. as well free us from our in-bred enemies to our Sion, to our grace and peace at home, as he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and all Iſrael from the Egyptian <hi>Shiſhak,</hi> a mighty for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign enemy abroad, could we act the ſame parts with them in godly ſorrow which brings ſalvation, 2 Cor. 7.10. as we re-act their ſins, yea,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116244:13"/>the very ſins of Sodom, Ezek. 16.49. Eſay 1.10. yea, though all things in Church and State ſeem to be luxate and diſ-joynted, as a body without nerves and ſinews, as once in Iſrael, when there was no King, Jud. 18.1. or as ſome ſay in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time, when the green blades were preferred before the riper heads, the young counſelling <hi>Phaetons</hi> before the ſolid Senatours, yea though all things, as ſome mutter, ſome vociferate, &amp; utter, ſeem to be turned <hi>ſuique deque,</hi> topſie turvie, upſide downe, in our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodized times by the wracks of warre, as if a diſh were turned with the bottome upward, and a ſhip with the ſails downward, in ſuch a <hi>Hyſteron Proteron,</hi> as few Ages have ever ſeen, chiefly Plebeian Owles throwing downe Eagles neſts, Crowes chattering, and Nightingales the ſweet ſingers of Iſrael, ſilent, learned and Orthodox Buclarks Cyphers, and Dolts and Dorbells Figures, knowledge a meere mute, and ignorance a ſounding Vowell, though never Conſonant, Mechanicall, blind arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance perking into <hi>Moſes</hi> his Chaire, with as much perill to muſhrump ungifted, uncalled uſurpers, both to their own ſoules and others, as once to leprous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> intruding into the Prieſts Office, 2 Chron. 26. to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> in ſtaying the tottering Ark without a call, 2 Sam. 6. to <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> in offering ſtrange fire, Lev. 10.1, 2. and to <hi>Dathan, Korah</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biram</hi> reſiſting proudly and rebelliouſly <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Numb. 16. as though they were dropt out of the clouds to curb, yea to cruſh both Magiſtracy and Miniſterie, which tooke too much upon them, and that they had ſuch a flaſh and flux of Revelations to guide and governe both themſelves and others for life and Doctrine, that Chriſt as <hi>Office perde,</hi> cleane out of Office, unable or unwiſe to rule Church or Commonwealth by his Powers or Ordinances ſecular or ſpirituall, might take them back againe to heaven if he would, and lock them as <hi>Aeolus</hi> the diſturbing winds into his owne cloſet, they had no more need of them then the Epheſians had of <hi>Pauls</hi> Goſpell, when they would cry up their <hi>Diana,</hi> Act. 17. then Idolatrous Iſrael had of <hi>Moſes</hi> when they cauſed <hi>Aaron</hi> to ſet them up a golden Calfe of their owne making, Exod. 32.3. then <hi>Iohn a Leyden, Knipperdolin,</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> had need of any other warrant from the word, but Revelations for maſſacring a hundred thouſand Commons beſides Nobles in their Ruſtick Belgick Warre, or then the Fratricelli, the Flagellants, the Beguardines, the Familiſts, the naked A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damites of latter times in Germany and Italy, with the Enthuſiaſts and David-Gorgians, the Swinekfeldians, and the Anabaptiſts, <hi>Michael Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus</hi> in Geneva, <hi>Gentilis</hi> in Berne, <hi>Iack Cade, Wat Tiler,</hi> and <hi>Straw</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>Ket</hi> the blaſphemous Arrian in Norfolk, <hi>Hacket</hi> once in London, yea <hi>Montanus</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> who both hanged themſelves in <hi>Tertullians</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116244:14"/>time, the Donatiſts and Circumcellians in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, or any that would ſet up thirteen or fourteen Religions in one Kingdom againſt one Truth, one Chriſt, one Salvation, Joh. 14.6. Eph. 4. all as erroneous as the Jewes Thalumd or Tucks Alchoran, and with as much warrant, as to grant thirteen wives to one husband, thirteen Suns in one Firmament, thirteen Kings in one Land, ſhould for all their folly, fantaſticalities, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, and hereſies of old, from hell new varniſht, ſtand any more in need of the Word, of Scripture, Counſells, Fathers, or Schooles of the Prophets, then of a ſixt-finger Revelations and a pretended ſpirit, like the Popes all-commanding unerring Authority in his Chaire muſt be the <hi>Domine fac totum,</hi> that which ſtrikes with the great ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hits the naile on the head, the great <hi>Apollo,</hi> the <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> the deciding Judge, the Oracle of truth; though from a Diabolicall <hi>Delphos</hi> from which there is no appeale, like <hi>Hercules</hi> his pillars, <hi>nè plus ultra,</hi> now I ſay though in ſuch Apoſtatizing in part or whole, many have forſaken their firſt faith, fallen from their firſt love, ſet up ſtrange Gods, ſtrange Idolls, even as Iſrael in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time were ſaid to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Law of the Lord, and the Lord to forſake them, 2 Chron. 12. yet there is hope in Iſrael, as repentance hath ever won what ſin hath loſt, as may be ſeen in <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> 2 Chron. 33.9, 10, 11, 12. in <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> Dan. 3. in the Ninevites, Ionas 3. in <hi>Peter,</hi> and oft in ſinning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting Iſrael, Iudg. 3.9 cap. 6.7. cap. 10. v. 10.</p>
            <p>So had we but Ninevehs and <hi>Rehoboams</hi> humiliations, 2 Chro. 12.6. why might not we have their exaltations? if we could ſow in tears, why might we not reape in joy? Pſa. 126.6. if we have a wet ſeed time, why might we not have a hopefull harveſt? if we did mourne, why might we not yet be comforted? Mat. 5.4. why might not all things proſper as in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time, ver. 12. and goe well with us, and with our poſterity? why might we not have Halcyon dayes after all theſe ſtorms and clouds? why might not our Horizon clear after all theſe ſhowres of bloud? why might we not, like a bone that is broke and right knit, be ſtronger then ever we were, both with God and man? Pſal. 51.8. could we with <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtle with God, we ſhould prevail with men yea with our foes, with our ſelves being our owne foes, as I hope by degrees to manifeſt, Gen. 32.28.</p>
            <p>Let the concluſion of this preſſed point be this, let us turne like Jordan and the red Sea backward, all the ſtreame and torrent of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility and hatred one to another, againſt our ſelves and our owne ſinne, which onely make us odious unto God, which are onely the <hi>Ates</hi> and Haggs, which throw the balls and brands (as Adultery betwixt man and wife) of diviſion betwixt God and us, Eſa. 59.2. take away the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116244:14"/>cauſe, and the effect will ceaſe; take the mote out of the eye, the thorne out of the heele, the thiefe out of the candle, the eye leaves watering, the heel rankling, and the candle ſmoaking: let us caſt our refractory <hi>Jonaſſes</hi> out of the Church, <hi>Achans</hi> out of the campe, <hi>Achitophels</hi> out of the Court, <hi>Sinons</hi> and Hereticall <hi>Simon Maguſſes</hi> out of our Cities, ſelf-ſeekers, finger-lickers, pence-ſpongers, ſtate-caterpillars, corrupt Officers out of place and grace, both in City and Country, chiefly every man hew every <hi>Agag</hi> in pieces at home, mortifie his owne luſts, put the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing knife of the word and ſpirit to his boſomed <hi>Delilah,</hi> his owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching domineering ſin that moſt reigns in him, or as an entertained ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is his familiar; and ſo all remoras &amp; obſtructions removed, the chamber of our hearts furniſhed for Chriſts cohabitation, Joh. 14.23. Rev. 3.20. as he lodged with <hi>Zachous,</hi> Luke 19. then he that is the Lord of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles will be ſure to keep them, the ſtrong armed man being thrown out, Luk. 11.22. we need no more then feare foes ſpirituall or corporall, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign or domeſtick, then one, of the ſons of <hi>Anak,</hi> or a <hi>Briarcus</hi> feares a Pygmie, then <hi>Ajax</hi> or <hi>Ashilles</hi> feared babling <hi>Therſites:</hi> will men both <hi>cominus</hi> and <hi>eminus,</hi> in offenſive and defenſive warres, fight for their own rights, and poſſeſſions: and will not the Lord of Hoſts hold his owne in us? will a Spaniard keep a Hold or Fort with tenacity, that he once poſſeſſeth? and as <hi>Jepthah</hi> told the King of Ammon, Jud. 11.24. will every man hold his owne, and keepe that which God hath given him, and will not God hold his owne? if we be his, will he ſuffer men to ſwallow us up quick, as the great Whale did <hi>Ionas?</hi> if God command us not to forſake our friend and our fathers friend, Prov. 27. he that hath been a friend to our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to <hi>David,</hi> and delivered them out of all their troubles, Pſal. 139.1. if we inſiſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſteps, Rom. 4 12. and be of the ſpirituall Houſe and heart of <hi>David,</hi> Zach. 12.10. he will alſo deliver us as he did them, according to his purpoſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Pſa. 34.18.19. he will not faile thee nor forſake thee, more then he did <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> cap. 1.5. Heb. 13.5. he will lift up himſelfe, and his ſtrength againſt thine enemies, Pſal. 7.6. he ſhall turne them backward, Pſa. 9.3. and breake the armes of then power, Pſa. 10.15. they ſhall fall into the pit that they have digged, and into the ſnare they have ſet for thee, as <hi>Faux, Garnet, Digby,</hi> and our Jeſuited powder Traytors were catcht in their own ſnares, Pſa. 9.10, 11. he will keep thee as the apple of his eye, and hide thee under the ſhadow of his wings, from the wicked that intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thee, Pſ. 17.9.10. though he come upon thee like a Lion greedy of his prey, v. 11.12. If God once ariſe, and be preſent with thee, thy enemies ſhall be ſcattered as the duſt and chaſſe before the wind, they ſhall vaniſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116244:15"/>as ſmoak, and melt as the wax before the fire, Pſa. 68.1.2. though they come about thee like Bees, or like Thornes, they are but a blaze, they ſhall be extinct.</p>
            <p>Call thou upon God in the day of thy trouble, that's thy duty; he will deliver thee, that's thy dignity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. Will the Regall Lion loſe life, but he will reſcue his Whelps if he heare them yell? and will not the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Tribe of Judah, to whom vengeance belongs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.1. avenge the cauſe of his little ones, who cry night and day unto him? Did not the Romans, the Athenians, and all the Pagans fight to the death <hi>pro focis,</hi> for their wives and children, as well as <hi>pro Aris,</hi> for their <hi>Paenates,</hi> their houſe Gods! Oh! if the Greeks were ſo incouraged in their <hi>Ajax</hi> and <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> the Trojans in their <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Troylus,</hi> the Philiſtines in their <hi>Goliah?</hi> and moſt Nations in the Colyphonians (though mercenary, like our Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers) if they could get them to ſtand for them? Shall not he that is arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>cap a pe,</hi> with the ſhield and buckler of faith, be confident of a Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie over every malignant enemy, externall, internall and infernall, that fights under the banners of <hi>Jehovah Elohim,</hi> the great Commander and diſpoſer of all created powers and natures, Angelicall, humane and belluine, from the Lion to the Worm, and the wretched Wren who can do a thouſand times more for his friends and favourites, then ever <hi>Achilles</hi> for his <hi>Patrocius,</hi> whoſe death he ſo revenged; or <hi>Hercules</hi> for his <hi>Theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> or <hi>Pirotheus,</hi> not being able to ſave himſelfe from the plots of <hi>Neſſus</hi> the Centaure, no more then <hi>Samſon</hi> (the Jewiſh <hi>Hercules</hi>) from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plottings of his Harlot and the Philiſtines againſt his life and liberty, <hi>Iud.</hi> 16.20. ſo unhappy is all humane power and ſtrength (as all may ſee in theſe two broken glaſſes) if God once leave it, as the German Phoenix <hi>Melancthon</hi> hath well obſerved: ſo happy are all thoſe true Iſraelites, true-hearted <hi>Nathanaels,</hi> patrizing with <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom God hath made a promiſe, that he will bleſſe thoſe who bleſſe them, and curſe thoſe who curſe them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. there being as it were a covenanted League (as now betwixt two Nations, and oft betwixt the Romans and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates) betwixt Chriſt and his Church, mutually to aid one another in all eſſayes and aſſaults. Oh! if the Saints be bleſſed who offer themſelves willingly to help the Lord, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9.23. it's no queſtion of the other aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliary; God will never be wanting to help them, <hi>ſecundum neceſſitatem, non voluntatem,</hi> according to their neceſſity, when God will, not according to their own will, (which is now the caſe of our Engliſh Sion) forbeggers muſt be no chooſers: <hi>Novit Medicus, non agrotus,</hi> our Phyſitian knowes better then we, poore impatient Patients, how and when to balme our long Phlebotomized bleeding times from our regnant crimes: we muſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116244:15"/>not indent nor articulate with the King of Kings, nor limit the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by our preſcriptions, as did the Bethulians, <hi>Iudith</hi> 7.30, 31. and that wicked <hi>Iehoram,</hi> 2 <hi>King</hi> 6.33. it is enough that he will not alwayes be plowing, and that the rod of the wicked ſhall not alwayes be upon the godly, but at laſt be burned, when his peccant children are ſcourged and humbled, upon his promiſes of deliverance, <hi>tandem aliquando,</hi> at his good leiſure and pleaſure, not at ours: In the interim, let every perplexed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit work upon this meditation, (even parallelling <hi>parvis magna,</hi> the ſtrong God with the weak arme of fleſh:) that if the Romans put ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull confidence in their <hi>Manlius,</hi> the defender of their Capitoll; in their <hi>Camillus,</hi> languiſhing Romes reſtorer; in their <hi>Marcellus,</hi> Romes ſword; in their <hi>Fabius,</hi> Romes <hi>Atlas</hi> againſt <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the Greeks in their <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> the prop and pillar: in their eloquent and thundering Orators <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Pericles,</hi> and of latter times the French in their <hi>Huon</hi> of Bourdeaux, their great <hi>Virago Jean de Pucill,</hi> but chiefly in their <hi>Charles</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Pipin,</hi> called the Hammer of their enemies; as the Germanes in their <hi>Otho</hi> the fourth, called for his victories, <hi>Mundi mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum,</hi> the wonder of the world; as the Hungarians once in their <hi>Hunni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades</hi> and <hi>Mathias,</hi> with others, whoſe Martiall exploits are famouſed in <hi>Plutark, Livie, A. Gellius,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Sabellicus,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Aeneid. c. <hi>13</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aventinus,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> 
               <hi>Pontanus,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">De Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine.</note> 
               <hi>Fulgoſus, Alex. ab Alexandro,</hi> lib 2. c. 11. and others, yea if our Engliſh were ſometimes ſo confident in the glories of our Nation, our <hi>Bevis</hi> of Hampton, our Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> and his Knights, our <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> ſon of <hi>Etheldred,</hi> called Iron ſides, our <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> the Conquerer of <hi>Corinaeus,</hi> and other ſubduers of men and monſters, yea, if we that were lately ſtormed and diſtreſſed in the Land of Ire by the numerous Rebells, were ſo happy in the ever ſucceſſefull valour and Heroick reſolves of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> the ſcourge Kerne as his Anagram beares it, and the terrour to the Rebells, as <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt once to the Turks, and our <hi>Talbot</hi> to the French, whoſe very name put them into a pannick feare, and made them fly as tripping Does and Raſcalls before our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Beagles into <hi>Tyrones</hi> old Forts of Woods and Bogs.</p>
            <p>I ſay, if there have been ſuch helps, ſuch hopes in all Ages, in armes of fleſh, in fraile men, whoſe breaths were in their noſtrills when God pleaſed to animate them, as Organs of doing good, or preventing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills in ſome States and Common-wealths, then rouzing our hearts a little higher, how much more hope and affiance ought we to place in the fountaine of ſtrength, then in the ſtreames? in the root and ſtrong bole,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116244:16"/>then in the weak and broken branches? in the primitive power, then in the derivative? in him that both in the Abſtract and Concrete is both power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and power it ſelf, both mighty and might it ſelfe, even omnipotent as well as omniſcious, and omnipreſent, who as by ſpeaking but a word he made the heavens, Gen. 1.15. calmed the Seas, turned the red Sea backward, Exod. 14.22. ſtayed the raging of the waves and winds, Mat. 8.26. caſt out Devils, Mark 1.26. cured the Leapers, Mark 1.40. raiſed the dead, Joh. 11.43, 44. recovered the Centurions ſervant, Mat. 8.8. hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all diſeaſes, Mat. 9.2.29. ſo if he ſpeake but the word he can ſheath the ſword, it ſhall not drink a drop of blood more: if we could but turne to him as we are injoyned, with rent hearts and broken, as corn in a Mill, and pepper in a Mortar, Joel 2.12. Pſa. 51.17. we ſhould by turning our mirth into mourning, Jam. 4.9. ſo turne his frownes into favours, his judgements into mercies, that in a trice his eare being not heavie to heare, Eſa. 59.2. more then in the like caſes with ours, 1 Sam. 7.6, 7, Judg. 2.5, 6, 7. &amp; cap. 20.26. with one word he would turn our ſtorms into calmes, our warres into peace, our ſighs into ſongs of deliverance; yea our Swords into Scythes, our Iron Helmets into Bee Hives, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of cruelty into inſtruments of mercies, our <hi>Mars</hi> into <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva,</hi> our Martiall Guns into Gownes: were but we turned as once <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 9.6. from Wolves to Lambs, from Goats to Sheep, from Newtralls and Laodiceans to anchored Zealiſts, yea from Lions and rearing Tygers, to Kids, living and loving together in a peace, inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly married unto grace, Eſa. 11.6, 7, 8. Oh! could we with the old yeare caſt away the old man, which is corrupt, and old faſhions and deceivable abhominable luſts, Col. 3.9. Eph. 4.22. Rom. 12.2. and with the new yeare put on Chriſt the new man, and be renewed in the inner man, Rom. 13.14. Eph. 4.23, 24. as the Serpent caſts off his old ſlough, the Stag his old head, the Colt his old haire, the Lobſters their old ſhells, the Eagle her old bill, whereby her age reneweth, and ſome men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren their old teeth, (rather then their old tongues) could we thus caſt off our abominations, Ezek. 18.31. our lying vanities, Jon. 2.8. our heart Idolls, Eſa. 31.7. our works of darkneſſe, Rom. 13.12. with hatred and indignation, in loathing and leaving every ſin, the true ſignall of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving repentance, 2 Cor. 7.10.11. how ſoon then would God caſt all our tranſgreſſions into the grave of his ſonne, into the midſt of the Sea as a milſtone, Micah 7.19. how ſoon would he make an act of oblivion, Ezek, 18.22. of all our former Delinquencies, how ſoon (contrary to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Foes, but ſuperficially reconciled) would he write our enmity in duſt, our repentance in braſſe? were we but once caſt in a new
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116244:16"/>mould, as old metalls broke melted and renewed, to ring better peales of prayers, and praiſes, how ſoon ſhould we be caſt into the armes of his mercies, that by a juſtifying faith having peace with him, Rom. 5.1. by our grand peace-maker, Eph. 2.14. we ſhould ſoon have peace one with another, though as yet there is no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God, Eſa. 57, 21. neither let us ever expect it, or deluſively dreame of it, ſo long as the Whoredomes and Witchcrafts of ſo many <hi>Jezabels</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, 2 King. 9.22. of he and ſhe, falſe Prophets, Rev. 2.20. as by ſuch old Hereſies new conjured up from hell, and ſuch new fantaſmes and fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries as Angells and men fearce ever heard before, the ſoules of ſo many millions are ſo poiſoned, their minds ſo diſtracted, and their inteſtine hatreds ſo inflamed one againſt another, more then ever the Samaritans againſt the Jewes, Joh 4.9. that <hi>Timpler, Althuſius, Arniſaeus, Tholoſanus, Bodin</hi> the French-man, our Engliſh <hi>Caſe,</hi> and all Politicians within the ſphere of my reading, ſhould be deceived, if <hi>Schiſma Eccleſiaſticum</hi> an Eccleſiaſticall Schiſme, as it is now the mother, ſo it do not continue as in all States where it kindles her wildfires) the Nurſe ſeminary and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellizer of <hi>Schiſma Politicum,</hi> of perpetuated factions, fractions, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and (Germany tells us) deſtructions alſo in our Common-wealths, and for my part I wiſh my predictions might prove as falſe, as they will be ſleighted, though as true as thoſe of <hi>Laomedon, Chalcas</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> which were not believed, till ſupine ſecure and incredulous Troy were fired, that the Toleration of many Religions in one Kingdome, which ſome would thruſt in upon us by head and ſhoulders, <hi>invita Minerva,</hi> without one breathing of the Spirit from the word, or the leaſt glimpſe of Conſcience grounded on Science, <hi>Conſcientia cordis ſcientia,</hi> taking light from the unerring Scriptures, as the Moon from the Sun, without which it is but like a Papall Purgatory, a Triton, a <hi>Chymaera,</hi> an opinion at beſt, or a phantaſme, that ſuch a Toleration of Liberty as the Libertines in Belgia once pleaded, and planted at laſt in bloud, in the Ruſtick war, will bring any more peace amongſt us, then betwixt <hi>Menclaus</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> ſtriving for one <hi>Helena;</hi> or betwixt the true Mother and the falſe in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> time, conteſting for one Child; or betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> bandying bloudy blows for one Supreme Power; or betwixt the ſeven Cities that conteſted for one <hi>Homer;</hi> or then was in Rome Papall, when three Anti-Popes, ſiring the whole Chriſtian world, run at Tilt for one Triple Miter; or then was betwixt <hi>Henry Monmouth,</hi> the right Heir to an Albion Crown, and <hi>Richard</hi> the Uſurper, when the ſword decided the undivided Scepter in Boſworth field: yea, no more probable peace amongſt many Religions, or indeed many painted errours, vanities, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116244:17"/>groſſe Hereſies, if not ſuch blaſphemies as in the Jewiſh Thalmud, or Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Alcoran, which (as our late powder Treaſon, the Iriſh Rebellion, <hi>Abſaloms</hi> conſpiracy, <hi>Ahabs</hi> aſſaſinating of <hi>Naboth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Read inſtances in</hi> Tholoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de rep. <hi>lib.</hi> 13. <hi>pag.</hi> 878. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 909. <hi>c.</hi> 8.903, 904, 905. Bodin de rep. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 547. Euſebius <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. Scorates <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>hiſt. c.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Herods</hi> intenſive butchering of the Bethlehem Babe, and the moſt peſtilent plots and deſignes for vile and ſiniſter ends, ever amongſt Jews, Turks, Chriſtians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, have ever been palliated and cloaked and vailed in the habit of Religion, and in the helmet of holineſſe and honeſty.</p>
            <p>I ſay all theſe Hydra-headed errours, different from truth, and from themſelves, will no more gain or retain any peace, with one true Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and Uniforme Religion, then there was peace amongſt the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified luſtfull Lovers of one <hi>Penelope,</hi> all hating <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> her legall husband, as well as one another; or then peace betwixt <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Achilles,</hi> about <hi>Briſeis; Troilus</hi> and <hi>Diomedes</hi> about one <hi>Creſſida; Turnus</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> about one <hi>Lavinia:</hi> alas ſuch Peace, (as any may foreſee a ſtorm, that ſees the pendent pitchy Cloud,) as hath been ever among the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh <hi>Ottomans,</hi> when he that prevailed in the Throne, whether juſtly or unjuſtly, ever either impriſoned, exoculated, or executed all the reſt of the Bloud-Royall, as <hi>Abimelech</hi> the bramble, dealt with all his Brethren, the ſons of <hi>Gideon,</hi> Judg. 9.5. and <hi>Jehu</hi> with all the ſons of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 Kings 10.17. or ſuch Peace between Hereſie and Truth as will ſet all on fire, Luk. 12.47. as would be between 6 or 7 Cocks of the game in one Pit, where they will either be all victors, or all die, though upon no other quarrell then Ambition, which domineers in Beaſts and men, but moſt in men metamorphoſed to Beaſts, by being brutized either by luſts in their life and converſation, or drunke with errours and ſtrange opinions, as a Crow with <hi>Nux vomica;</hi> even to reeling, and ſtaggering, and occaſioning or cauſing a whole Kingdom to reel, ſtagger, and totter with them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ruination, <hi>quod omen avertat Deus:</hi> which to prevent, let us halt no more betwixt two opinions, nay betwixt more opinions then colours in the Rain-bow, if not then <hi>Argus</hi> eyes in the Peacocks traine: if every Babilon and every <hi>Baal,</hi> every reared <hi>Dagon,</hi> be God or for God, or from God, adhere to it, 1 Kin. 18.21. but if God be God, and there be but one God, <hi>ipſiſſima veritas,</hi> as one eſſentiall ſoule, ſaving truth, and but one true way of worſhipping this God, in ſpirit and truth, John 4.23, 24. as there is but one ſoul and ſpirit in man to be ſaved by this right worſhip, without will worſhips, Papiſticall, Phariſaicall, or Schiſmaticall, and if this God will admit no corrivalls in a Church or ſtate (as was told the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116244:17"/>Romane Senate, that Chriſt would have no copartnerſhip with their Paganiſh Gods,) yea if this God hate all plowing with an Oxe and a Horſe, all ſowing with miſcellanian ſeeds, all linſey-woolſey weavings; all compounded, interwoven, intermixed Worſhips in a hotch-potch, and a galley-mawfrey Religion, as hee is a pure and ſimple Spirit, no more mixing with falſe Spirits of lies and errours, then fire with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, oyle (which ever ſwims above) with any poyſoned liquids: if it be thus with God, then let my pen, as well as tongue, in preſſe, pew, and Pulpit, preach to all <hi>John</hi>-indifferents, all Scepticks, all Seekers for any new Religion, as if they went yearly or monethly to Poland, or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam, or Holland, to ſeeke a new one, or were white paper, fit to take any print or blot, or wax for any ſeale, new veſſels for any ſeaſoning, ſweet or ſower, with wine or vinegar: let me ſay to ſuch, even what Chriſt preached to Sathan himſelfe, who is a liar in the tongues of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as well as a murtherer in the ſwords of Tyrants, John 8.44. doe thou worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only do thou ſerve, Mat. 4.10. ſo ſhalt thou gain ſuch figs from thiſtles, ſuch fruits from foes, both to thy body and ſoul, goods, goodneſſe and good name, that though the Land ſhould be darke like Egypt, yet thou ſhalt find a lightſome Goſhen in thine owne ſoule, Exod. 10.23. thy fleece ſhould be wet like <hi>Gideons,</hi> with the dews of grace, though the whole Kingdome ſhould be as dry and barren as the ſands of Africk: thou ſhouldſt be as a cube or ſquare, <hi>undique quadratus,</hi> to fall right and ſtraight, which way ſoever the many headed multitude moved, right or wrong; thou ſhouldſt bee fixed as the two poles, the Axhurried as in a ratling Coaeltrees of Heaven, which way ſoever the ſcopperill and whirligig times did volve and rowle, thou ſhouldeſt caſt the Anchor of truth in our tempeſtuous ſeas, in the high ſwoln waves of all wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blown-opinions, ruffling in ſuch fierce and furious oppoſition; yea if thy wayes do pleaſe the Lord, thy enemies ſhall be at peace with thee: Let theſe curative cordials, be as words ſpoken to the weary in dueſeaſon, let them be as apples of gold, with pictures of ſilver to refreſh him who ſaith with <hi>Gideon,</hi> if the Lord be with me, why then is all this evill befallen me? Judg. 6.13. why goe I thus heavily oppreſſed with my foe? as <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> was provoked by her adverſary, to make her fret, 1 Sam 1.6. how long ſhall mine enemy be exalted over me, Pſa. 13.2. how long ſhall my falſe familiar friend, my <hi>Junior Achitophel</hi> plot miſchiefe againſt me? yea, being unequallly yoaked with a <hi>Zipporah,</hi> or a <hi>Xantippe,</hi> my <hi>uxor,</hi> my vexer, how doe I wear a ſtrait pinching ſhoe, yet unleſſe I goe barefoot and wear upon the hoof, I cannot put it off, no more then the horſe in the Fable could put out of his mouth the curbing bitt, or throw off the ſaddle
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116244:18"/>of ſervitude which man his rider and derider put upon him, when he was once as free as the wild Stag and Buck upon the wide mountaines, ere he fooliſhly vaſſalized himſelfe, like an infranchized free-man made a ſlave? Oh how long ſhall I hold a Wolfe by the eares, if I hold him he bites, if I let him goe and reſiſt him, he worries? how long ſhall I be hurried as in a ratling Coach, or toſſed ſhip, which way I would not: yet if I leap out, I break my leg or neck by land, or drowne by ſea? <hi>quo me vertam neſcio,</hi> doe what I can, I faile betwixt <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis,</hi> I ſplit on one rock or other: my propoſed ſalves will be as ill as my ſores, like <hi>Androdus</hi> the Roman: I am fed as in the Lions Den; all the waies I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to helpe my ſelfe, ſeem to me as deſparate as to him who cut off his great Toes to cure the Gout, yea, leaping as it were out of the frying-pan into the fire, lik to the Flounder, <hi>a malo ad pejus,</hi> from evill to worſe; for eſcaping (with ſuch difficulty and danger, as the Hare from the Hounds) from the Iriſh Caniballs and Nimrodians, thinking here to ſwat &amp; tapez ſafely, I have in two or three places ſheltred my ſelfe as the ſheep under brambles and briers with ſome torne fleece, if not fleſh; and at this inſtant I and my poor periſhing Children, roaſting as at a lingring ſire, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and conſuming by degrees, as Lampes goe out wanting Oyle; wee cry for bread as hungry Birds to their Dams, and children to dry nurſes, yea as Priſoners in Ludgate to Adders eares: while the corne (ſaith <hi>vox populi</hi>) to feed us reaped in a ſilver Harveſt in Holland and in England, is either (as is <hi>vox loculi</hi>) put into private poakes, from whence like the prey in the Lions paw, there is <hi>reductio perimpoſſibile,</hi> or elfe diverted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, as if <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould be rob'd to pay <hi>Paul;</hi> and further this is my miſery, that though <hi>venter non habet aures,</hi> the belly hath no eares, and thoſe that grieve muſt groan; yet if hunger the worſt of all plagues as <hi>Homer</hi> calls it, find but a complaining tongue, it's probable to get me a bolted heel: if I do but vent my mind, my wind, like the Whale and the Otter in the water, and the Moal above the Earth, I may be ſtruck with the ſharp ſpear of conſtruction or correction. Oh is there any hope in Iſrael for theſe harmes? any balm in Gilead for theſe griefs? any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridate for theſe maladies, miſeries? any Roſes from theſe pricks, cries Pierce Pennileſſe) Oh yes: for if we beleive <hi>Dioſcorides Dodoneus,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>F. B.</hi> Centuries, Roſes grow beſt and ſmell ſweeteſt, neer unto ſtrong ſented Onions and Garlick, yea we ſee amongſt Nettles and Thornes: and it is obſerved by Herbaliſts, that thoſe Roſes that are without pricks, as your wild Cop-roſes in cornes, and Canker-roſes in hedges, are ill ſented and good for nought, baſe (as excellent Emblemes of proſperity and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) in reſpect of thoſe with pricks, excellent in colour, odoriferous in ſmell,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116244:18"/>which though they oft grow low, and amongſt thornes, yet exceed your canker-roſes high bloom'd in hedges, as much as a ſcale weighed downe with gold is above a ſcale fild with feathers and fuzballs, which flurts up like ſome light heads, from low barnes, chaires and tubs, as high as <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's</hi> pulpit, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.4.</p>
            <p>O it is a comfortable truth, which is affirmed and confirmed from many examples in all ages by the beſt Belgick Divines,<note n="a" place="margin">Melancthon in poſtillis part. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>4.37.</hi> &amp; in locis, fol. <hi>466.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 241.</note> in his Colloquies; <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellius</hi> in his Chronicles<note n="c" place="margin">Part. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>351.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>51</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigfridus Saccus</hi> in his Poſtils<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 126.</note>, with others; that as Roſes grow the beſt with pricks and among thornes, Onions beſt and biggeſt in ſtormes and tempeſts<note n="e" place="margin">Pezelius de Margaritis c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the Palme tree (according to <hi>Pliny</hi>) <hi>in terra ſalſa &amp; nitroſa,</hi> in a ſalt earth, and when it is moſt preſt with weight, according to the old verſe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nititur in pondus palma, &amp; conſurgit in altum,</l>
               <l>Quo magis &amp; premitur, hoc mage tollit onus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yea as it is green like the Lawrell in winter as well as in Summer, and buds againe <hi>ſucciſa &amp; emortua,</hi> when cut, and ſeemingly dead, with many other rarities in it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Camerarius</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 84. <hi>pag.</hi> 472.</note> in his Centuries: ſo the Church of Chriſt, and every true Chriſtian is and hath been ever more glorious under the Croſſe, under Tyrants, Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Hereticks, (the three great peſts and plagues of the Church now) as they have been ever, (if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Hemingius</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">In his Poſtils fol. <hi>264.269.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gualter</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">In Mat. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Strigellius</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">In Argum. Pſal. <hi>28.</hi> &amp; <hi>83.</hi> fol. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">In his Poſtils part. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>585.</hi>
               </note>) then when it had moſt reſt and peace, it increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more, and budding more under <hi>Nero, Domitian, Decius, Iulian, Maximinus, Genſericus, Theodorick</hi> and other Pagan and Arrian perſecutors, when it was water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and grew by the bloud of the Martyrs, as both <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Plures effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimur quoties metimur.</note>, and <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Lib. hiſt. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>, yea experience have obſerved, then when it had moſt reſt and peace under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and other Halcyon dayes of tranquillity, when Hereſies were hatcht like Summer Gnats in heats and Sunſhines: and at laſt the Antichriſtian Pope, from ambition of Prelates and Patriarchs for ſuperiority<note n="o" place="margin">See Morney de progreſſu Papatus.</note>, when Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion begot riches, and the daughter viper-like devoured the mother: when proſperity (like the Sun which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Traveller in <hi>Plutarch</hi> to caſt off his cloke) made men caſt off the true worſhip of God, and adverſity (like the raine, which made him<note n="f" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116244:19"/>buckle his cloke to him) cauſed men to cleave cloſer towards God, even as <hi>Iacob</hi> was more glorious in his viſion of Angells when he lay in the open fields with a ſtone under his head, then when he poſſeſſed Canaan, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.11, 12. <hi>Noah</hi> more glorious pent a whole yeare in the Arke, preſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong wild beaſts, then when he planted vines and was drunk, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1. c. 8.1. cap. 9.20, 21. ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> was moſt glorious in priſon, where God revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led dreames unto him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his exile in Pathmos, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Revelations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. The children of Iſrael in the red Sea, where they had their preſervation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. In the wilderneſſe, where Manna from heaven was their meat, and the rock gave them drink, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. The captived Jewes in Babylon, where God ſtir'd them up ſuch excellent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as <hi>Daniel, Ezekiel, Zachary, Haggai,</hi> and propagated his worſhip by them to Kings and Kingdomes. And as Chriſt himſelfe was more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious on the Croſſe, then when the Jewes entertained him with their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna's, <hi>John</hi> 12.14. for then the Centurion, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.47. <hi>Pilates</hi> wife, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.15. the darkneſſe of the earth, <hi>Marke</hi> 15.33. the eclipſed Sun, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.15. the earthquake, the opened graves, the veile of the Temple, and the rocks rent, verſ. 51, 52. teſtified his innocency, as alſo <hi>Iudas</hi> his betrayer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.4. and the thief that was crucified and converted, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.43. ſo if thou be a true diſciple of this Maſter, a living member of this myſticall Head, and not as a wooden leg, and a glaſſie eye, liveleſſe and ſenſleſſe: the more thy enemies ſeek to cloud thee, the more thou ſhalt ſhine, like ſtarres in a darke night: the hotter the furnace of their wrath, the more ſhall the gold of thy Faith be purified: the more the winds blow, the more Oake like ſhalt thou be fixed and rooted in thy holy reſolutions, 2 Sam. 6.20, 21. as <hi>David</hi> by the mocks of <hi>Michal:</hi> the more thy foes rub thee like a Pomander, yea pounce thee in the mortar of their malice, the ſpices of thy graces ſmell the ſweeter: the more that Sathan and his Organs winnow thee, the leſſe chaffe they leave in thee; the more thy Kitchin-ſculs ſcum thee and ſcour thee as a veſſel of Honour, the brighter they make thee: the tongues of theſe Dogs, theſe Cerberized whelpes, doe but medicinably lick the ſores of thy ſins, as once the ulcers of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> their Gall and Aloes doth but imbitter the dugs of the world to thee, that Chriſt may be more ſweet; theſe bug-beares do but make thee cry and fly into the armes of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp; faelix crux quae ducit ad Christum,</hi> it is a happy Croſſe which drives thee, yea drawes thee nearer unto Chriſt; it is no matter how fierce and rough the winds be, that drive the loaden ſhip ſooner and ſafer into her Haven, the Port of Peace.</p>
            <p>The concluſion of all is to prevent confuſion, we may be wronged
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116244:19"/>by others, hurt only by our ſelves, others may plunder our goods, but ſo long as the fleſh is ſound the ſilver feathers may grow againe, as in <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, Job 42.10. the Devill himſelfe could not hurt <hi>Job,</hi> nor his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wife, though called the Devills Dam, <hi>Naomi</hi> that is emptie may be full againe, Ruth 1.21. however, thou runneſt thy race never worſe to heaven, though thon wanteſt thy trappings and golden Boſſes, and though thou beeſt in as great exigents as once <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 21.3. &amp; ca. 25.8. and as <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 King. 17.12, 13. to beg thy bread of ſome <hi>Nabal,</hi> ſome poor Widdow, yea as poore as <hi>Job</hi> on the dunghill, or as once Chriſt thy Maſter, Luk. 9.58. yet in all this not forſaken, Pſa. 37.21. the Lord forſakes not his Saints, V. 28. though the Lions lack and ſuffer hunger, yet they ſhall not want, Pſal. 34.10. though they gather but a little Manna it ſufficeth, Exod. 16.18.20. godlineſſe with contentation is enough, 1 Tim. 6.8. God can bleſſe to them a little meale, a little oyl in a cruſe as to two poor Widdowes, 1 King. 17.13. 2 King. 4.2. a little pulſe to <hi>Daniel,</hi> cap. 1.12.13. as ſometimes a few Turnops and Potatoes, when we were beſieged in Ireland as well as a ſtalled Oxe. There is one Pearle even for a Prince which cannot be plundered, it adornes a Crown though beſet with Thornes, and this Pearle is patience, a great poſſeſſion unto all, as Chriſt calls it, Luke 21.19. a rich dowry to a Widdow as poore as <hi>Ruth,</hi> a poſſeſſion out of which the Devill himſelfe could not diſpoſſeſſe <hi>Job,</hi> c. 1.22. withall, thou mayeſt be wronged in thy name, a <hi>Joſeph</hi> may be falſly accuſed, a <hi>Cato,</hi> a <hi>Scipio,</hi> an <hi>Abner,</hi> a <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> a <hi>Phocion,</hi> a <hi>Socrates,</hi> yea the beſt Patriots and Patricians may be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, an <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> an <hi>Eugenius,</hi> a <hi>Narciſſus</hi> may be ſcandalized in life and Doctrine by the Arrians, as was <hi>Calvin, Beza, Luther,</hi> our beſt Belgick Divines, by <hi>Cocleus, Bolſecus, Scurrilous Kelliſon, Endemon, (Caco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demon,)</hi> and other Romiſh <hi>Rabſhakehs:</hi> but what of this? is an Eagle hurt by the chartering of a Crow? or a Lion by the yelps of a Curre? doth the Moon ſhine leſſe though the Dogs of Egypt bark at it? can earthly or lunatick interpoſitions long ecclipſe the Sunſhine of the Saints? we have heard of a Grandee which wiſhed his man to call him Knave, and then ſhakt the lap of his Gowne, and what was he worſe for it? words are but wind, they breake no bones, <hi>quid male feci,</hi> what evill have I done may any <hi>Plato</hi> ſay, that a bad man ſpeakes well of me, <hi>de me male dicunt aſt mali,</hi> God will doe <hi>David</hi> good, even <hi>eo nomine,</hi> becauſe <hi>Shimei</hi> reviles him, 2 Sam. 16.12.</p>
            <p>Beſides thou art impriſoned, yea <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> may be ſo far wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as whipt in priſon, Act. 16. yet not hurt, theſe bleſſed Birds ſing ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tones in their cages, v. 25. then ever the birds of <hi>Hanno</hi> or <hi>Sapho;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116244:20"/>thou mayeſt be alſo ſo farre wrong'd, as to be baniſhed thy Countrey, and bandied, and racketed from poſt to pillar, and find no reſt like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove, to the ſoale of thy foot, yet not hurt, ſo long as thou findſt reſt in Chriſt, ſo long as the Spirit doth viſit thee in thy Pathmos, Rev. 1.10, 11. <hi>omne ſolum forti Patria,</hi> the Sun ſhines every where, and God is found in every Countrey, indeed could thy foes baniſh God from thee, as thy ſinnes doe, thy worſt foes, then thy caſe were lamentable, as once <hi>Sauls,</hi> 1 Sam. 16.14. &amp; cap. 28.15, 16.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, thy foes may take away thy life, yet they hurt thee not, onely ſin hurts thee, that deprives thee of the life of grace and of the life of glory, that deads thy ſoule here, Epheſ. 2.1. Luk. 6.60. and damnes it hereafter, Rom. 6.23. it is onely ſinne the ſting of death which hurts thee, 1 Cor. 15.55, 56. which ſting being taken away by Chriſt, thou maiſt put this ſtingleſſe Bee in thy boſome, v. 57. death is to thee a ſweet ſleep, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay 57.2. a bleſſed reſt, Rev. 14.13. in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, Luk. 16.22. in theſe and whatever elſe is obnoxious to humane nature, the Saints are Conquerors, Rom. 8.37. now did Conqueſts ever hurt a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> a <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey,</hi> a <hi>Lucullus,</hi> a <hi>Fabius?</hi> doe all things health, wealth, poverty, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, life, death, friends, foes, worke together for the good of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, Rom. 8.28. as all the Phyſicall Simples in a compound for the good of a Patient? all the Starres and Planets by their influence, for the good of theſe ſublunary bodies? and can that which works for our good doe us hurt, unleſſe we hurt our ſelves? as indeed we doe, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worſt foes we have from home with us, yea carrying them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with us as Snakes in our boſomes to ſting us, our ſinnes our darling regnant unmortified ſinnes bred in our ſoules, theſe and onely theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Achans</hi> in our Camps to diſturb us, the <hi>Sinons</hi> in our Cities, chiefely in our Troynovant, yea the Quoy-ducks, the <hi>Dalilahs</hi> in our Families, our Chambers, our Cloſets, to betray us, the vipers which breed within our bowells, the wormes within our intralls, the Fleſh Wolves within our fleſh which corrode us, yea kill us, the <hi>Cantharides</hi> in our oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſoile us, to ſpoile us, the Moaths in our Garments to fret us, the Midianites amongſt us to vex us, the Canaanites in our borders, as pricks in our ſides and thornes in our eyes, Judg. 2.31. to torture us, to torment us: that of <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> being to me oraculous, truer then from <hi>Delphos,</hi> that <hi>nemo laeditur niſi à ſeipſo,</hi> hone is hurt but by himſelfe, by his owne ſinnes, as <hi>Noah</hi> was drunke with his owne wine, Gen. 9.22. <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſes</hi> ſlaine with his owne ſword, <hi>Marlow</hi> ſtabbed with his owne Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo we are ſlaine by our owne luſts which fight againſt our ſoules, 1 Pet. 2.11. and vaſſallize us as they did <hi>Hercules, Sampſon, Alexander,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116244:20"/>Caeſar, Hannibal, Achilles,</hi> and the greateſt Conquerers, who were ſlaves to their owne unlimited luxuries, as I could largely Hiſtorifie them and Parallel our very poſtures and preſſures with that fond horſe in the Fable, bred neare the ſmoaks and fogs of ſome thick aire, not on the pure airy Mountaines with the wily Stag, who ſuffering man to ride him, being as free as the Buck, was ſo vaſſallized by man his rider and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he could never yet for all his fretting at his owne folly, put the curbing bit out of his mouth, nor ſhake the ſaddle of ſubjection from his back.</p>
            <p>Oh! we are ſlaves to our luſts, as that great <hi>Alcides</hi> to his <hi>Dianira,</hi> to him <hi>Deiira,</hi> theſe are the Lord-Danes which rule us as by armed Law, either we cannot or will not reſiſt them; theſe are to us like Traytors bred in the breaſts and boſomes of Kings, yea as Favourites growing up by their Kings, as Ivies by ſtrong Oakes, and Elder Trees in and by walls, yet bringing them downe by whom they grew, and every way as fatall to them as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> once to <hi>Solomon</hi> and his houſe, <hi>Cleander Phrix</hi> to <hi>Comodus, Philip Arabs</hi> to <hi>Gordianus, Calippus</hi> to <hi>Dion, Phocus</hi> to <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Giges</hi> to <hi>Candaulus,</hi> and our Court <hi>Ganimede Gaveſton</hi> once to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſecond, with many more recorded by <hi>Tholoſanus</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, l. 22. p. 1403, 1409. <hi>Guicciardine</hi> in his Politikes, part 2. p. 94. and the French <hi>Bodin</hi> in his republick lib. 6. c. 5. p. 1154. with others, whoſe fates and falls to prevent, ſince a volumn might be multiplied, what States and Potentates ſuch ſins have ruinated, as are regnant at this inſtant both in our Church, State, Countries, and Cities; let us cruſh them as Cockatrices in their ſhells, and Serpents in their heads; let us put the ſacrificing knife of the Word to their throats, and mortifie them by the Spirit, Rom. 8.13. ſo killing theſe vipers that will otherwiſe kill us, we ſhall gain, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Grace and Peace with God, with man, and with our ſelves, even Peace externall, internall, eternall: chiefly let us cloſe haſtily, heartily with Chriſt our Peace, Eph. 2.14. with <hi>Simeon</hi> let us claſpe him in the arms of an applying faith, Luke 2.28. then we ſhall be ſure to find Sun-ſhine in our Rains, ſongs in our ſighs, calmes after ſtormes, peace after warres: in this Sun we ſhall have all light, in this Manna all meat, in this fountain all refreſhing waters of life, John 4.10. in our dead times, <hi>Deus meus &amp; omnia,</hi> ſaid a Martyr) my God and all things, my Rock, Refuge, Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and Salvation, Pſal. 18.1. <hi>Ieſus esto mihi Ieſus,</hi> O Saviour be to me a Saviour, AMEN, AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 29. 1647.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:116244:21"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript to the candid Reader.</head>
            <p>THough the Authours eye is ſaid to perfect the Preſſe, as the Masters eye to fat the horſe, yet ſome Errataes may ſcape the eyes of an <hi>Argus,</hi> as <hi>pag. 15. lin. 25. effects</hi> for <hi>affects,</hi> in ſuch venialls thou art deſired to wink at ſmall faults: as alſo, <hi>p. 32.</hi> and <hi>p. 37.</hi> the Fable of the ſadled Horſe, and the wily unſubjected Stag, are by our over-ſight twice reflexed upon, perhaps uſefull to ſome that read the Riddle right, though <hi>decies repetita,</hi> though to a too criticall Carp-fiſh, <hi>bis repetita ſordent.</hi> Others liking (as our Iriſh their Rainebow Butter above Veniſon) ought ſlubbered in Preſſe or Pulpit in a Luxate ſtile, ſavouring of <hi>Gregory</hi> Non-ſenſe better then ought reliſhing of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> Lamp-oyle, <hi>Lipſius</hi> his <hi>Multa paucis,</hi> or <hi>Chriſoſtomes</hi> and <hi>Chriſologus</hi> golden tongues, or poliſht by Chriſts owne Scribe, preſcribed to bring out of his treaſure things old and new: before whom in this antipodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed age, where light heeles go up, and grave heads down, every green blads, though died black or block, is preferred, if but Lettice for Schiſmaticall lips. And to ſpeak where the ſhoe pincheth, as juſt (or unjuſtly) now I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment what I write Fruits of, and from Foes, though as the Swan and Peacock I am ſo conſcientious to my black feet, that I am not proud of reall or imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary faire feathers, of too much reading Hiſtory and eloquence, of which factious Hot-Spurs falſly would cry me ſo guilty, that as though ſtore were a ſore, for this they frisk from me, perhaps to ſome Doctor <hi>Dulman</hi> in a gray coat with a groſſe note, and on ſuch frivolous pretexts go about to divorce me once more from my <hi>Brides,</hi> to whom I offer to demonſtrate againſt all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, that above all Miniſters I have as lawfull a call as <hi>Collatine</hi> to his <hi>Lucrece,</hi> though any young <hi>Tarquin</hi> who had need ſtay at Jerico till his beard and braine be growne, ſhould offer to raviſh her from me, whoſe heart I have ten to one above any intruder, yea though his factious Favourites (like the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſons of <hi>Brutus</hi>) ſhould arme his uſurpations by a miſinformed Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary power, againſt my life or Doctrine, <hi>in cauſa inaudita,</hi> in defect of ſuch a Juſtice as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> taxed in the Jewes, and <hi>Paul</hi> found in <hi>Felix, Feſtus,</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> though Pagans, to be condemned ere I ſpeake, yet once heard I here pawne that very blood which I have ventured for them more then any Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in three Climes, that I deſerve more gratefull regard and reward then by unjuſt divorcing me from my Miniſteriall marriage, to be expoſed to ſcorne, impoveriſhing and perſecutions verball and reall, yea to fly for means, without cauſe ſhown why, in the winter of the yeare, and of my yeares; If this be not <hi>ſummum jus, &amp; dare veniam corvis, vexat cenſura columbos,</hi> I am like my ſucceſſor <hi>Ignoramus:</hi> to ſay no more: yet <hi>jacta eſt alea, pejo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra tuli, majora meliora ſpiro ſpero. Hercules invidiam ſupremo fine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavit. Ah ſi fas dicere, ſed fas—in utramque paratus,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Reſolute <hi>Hierom</hi> againſt the diſſolute times.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
